<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two treatises the first, entituled, The foode of the faithfull. The second Deaths welcome.</title>
            <author>Garey, Samuel, 1582 or 3-1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01475</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115877</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851094</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851094</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16349</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01475)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16349)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1099:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two treatises the first, entituled, The foode of the faithfull. The second Deaths welcome.</title>
                  <author>Garey, Samuel, 1582 or 3-1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 29, [3]; 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. R[oberts] for Iefferie Chorlton [sic],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Ann Dom. 1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: S.G., i.e. Samuel Garey.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first treatise has caption title reading: "The food of the soul"; the second has separately dated title page reading: "A short and necessary treatise entituled: Deaths welcome".</note>
                  <note>Separate register and pagination.</note>
                  <note>Some pages marked.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Future life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16349:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16349:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO Treatiſes, THE FIRST, EN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, THE FOODE OF the Faithfull.</p>
            <p>THE SECOND Deaths welcome.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by I. R. for <hi>Iefferie Charlton.</hi> Anno Dom. 1605.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16349:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16349:2"/>
            <head>To the right honorable <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Garrarde,</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>Garrardes Bromley:</hi> and to the right worſhipfull his brother in law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Sir <hi>Peter Leigh</hi> of Lime, <hi>I. C</hi> wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth health, honor, &amp; happineſſe in this life, and in the life to come.</head>
            <p>I <hi>Socrates</hi> the Athenians Orator (right honorable) calleth Nobilitie the pillar of learning, and <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith, that a true noble man is a faithfull fauorite of the learned. And for this reaſon the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, Orators, Poets, Diuines, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther writers, conſecrate their labors to the Patronage of ſuch worthymen, who are placed in the high ſobeare of greatneſſe, and ſeated in the Throne of Nobilitie, who can with power, and may with au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie defend them vnder the fauorable winges of their ſafe protection. In like
<pb facs="tcp:16349:3"/>manner, I who am neither ſound Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher, nor eloquent Orator, nor good Poet, nor profound Diuine, haue preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to dedicate to your gracious viewes, theſe two Treatiſes (whoſe rudeneſſe are far vnſutable to weare the Liueries of your names) for two eſpeciall conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The firſt is, becauſe you two be the great fauorits of learning, and in you liue the ſparkes of <hi>Augustus</hi> liberallitie, to cherriſh the Muſes, who now for want of ſuccor are almoſt famiſhed. The ſecond is, which mooueth me moſt of all, to giue you a liuing memoriall of the louing duty I bare to your honored deceaſed mother, vnto whom for many ſingular good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors, I will euer recogniſe my ſelfe infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitly bounden, for whoſe ſake I ſuppoſe I haue paſſed the bonds of modeſty in this preſumptious attempt. Yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding perſwaded by my friends earneſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties, and mooued by that priuate du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie which I owe, to that vertuous Lady your mother (who is now a cohabitor with God) I haue emboldened my baſhfull nature, and as he ſaith, <hi>Commaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culaui frontem pudoris limites tranſilire.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb facs="tcp:16349:3"/>therefore (moſt renowned Patrons) this gratefull teſtimonie of my dutie, and thankfulneſſe, which I tender for mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold benefits vnto you both, whom I make as honorable twinns vnited in the vnion of my zealous, and duteous affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: I confeſſe it is a trifle, nor a fit ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to be bee viewed by your ſeuere eies, yet I hope you will receiue it as a token, and earneſt pennie of my long concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led loue, and dutie, according to your accuſtomed, and incomparable gentel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: <hi>Phillip</hi> of Maccedon did accept a bunch of grapes giuen by a Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaine; and <hi>Apollo</hi> did vouchſafe to take a wodden diſh as a great gift. So I truſt that you (ſithence my abilitie ſerueth to no better purpoſe, nor you expect a kind of remuneration) will receiue it in curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manner, and grant this abortiue brat (which ſhould haue wanted a Godfather, had I not choſen you) to ſhelter vnder the defenſiue ſhadowes of your patronage, giuing it the Almes of your approouiug commendation, to cloath the naked beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie of his threed-bare inuention: which if it ſhall pleaſe your good honors to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:16349:4"/>like <hi>Minerua,</hi> this forſaken deformed Owle, vnder the ſure target of your tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſhall be as ſecure from Critickes, as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> was free from the Greekes, being defended with <hi>Aiax</hi> buckler. So hoping of your wiſhed defence, I commit it with all ſubmiſſion to your protection, ſaying, that which <hi>Gratian</hi> ſayd to his Patron, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>obis ſoluo quod debebam, et ad huc debeo quod ſoluam.</hi> So duly, and daily praying for you, and yours, I humbly take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your honors in all duty to commaunde. I. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:16349:4"/>
            <head>Honoratiſsimo viro Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no <hi>Gerardo,</hi> omnibus ſapientiae, et virtutis luminibus clariſsimo.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>TE mea ſi tantum anderet ſperare patronum</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dum</hi> optaret (rustica Muſa) ſibi.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gerardu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi> (at que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, phoebe viru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) qui lumine me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis</l>
               <l>excellit Phoebum, Phoebigenumque chorum.</l>
               <l>O quem te memorem? Phoebum? tu doctior illo.</l>
               <l>Mercurium? linguae laurea danda tibi.</l>
               <l>Catonem? longe ſuperas conſultus agendo.</l>
               <l>an Maecenatem? laudat Apollo magis:</l>
               <l>Ergo <hi>Gerardus</hi> eris, quo dicinomine gandent,</l>
               <l>Macenas, Phoebus, Mercuriuſque, Cato.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>MIte ſupercilij iubar, iubarque ſororum,</l>
               <l>Et decus Auglorum, preſentis gloria ſaecli,</l>
               <l>Spe maguus, fama melior, virtutibus amplus,</l>
               <l>Gratus ades, nostris falix allabere captis,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine meis, ſed nec curabis vivere mecum,</l>
               <l>Aeternum victure tuis <hi>(Gerarde)</hi> trophais.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:16349:5"/>
            <head>Ad digniſsimum, et clariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum Equitem <hi>Petrum Leigh.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>BEnignitate, gloria,</l>
               <l>honore, claritudine,</l>
               <l>tuum praeeſſe cateris</l>
               <l>ſit omen. Places Deo,</l>
               <l>places patriae omnibuſque:</l>
               <l>faues literis, foues literatos:</l>
               <l>hae metae honoris: macte:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Spice laetanti librum (digniſſime) vultu,</l>
               <l>quo fallas vitae taedia longa breuis.</l>
               <l>Hic Christus ſatiat ſitibundas ſanguine fauces,</l>
               <l>et prandere iubet corpore famelicos.</l>
               <l>Accipe gratuito caelestia fercula Christi</l>
               <l>hoſpitium caelum, Christus et hoſpes erit.</l>
               <l>Menſa itidem caelum, conuiuae deniquae ſancti,</l>
               <l>vt ſedeas, gustes, prouocat ipſe Deus.</l>
               <l>Nileſt quod renuas, nam dantur pharmaca me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis,</l>
               <l>haec medicina animae, pharmacopola Deus.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:16349:5"/>
               <l>Qui te faelicem, lata<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tem, glorifie antem,</l>
               <l>corpore, mente, polo, per ſua philtra dabit.</l>
               <l>Ergo laudetur, placeat, metuatur, ametur,</l>
               <l>hoſpès et hòſpitium, phármacepola, Dèus.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16349:6"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>MAy I preſume (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) out of my penurie, to throw a mite into the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie of the Church, when others which haue larger talents, bury the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſilence, nor will let theyr labors be peruſed by the common <hi>Argos</hi> of the vngratefull multitude: yet I like a blind <hi>Babius,</hi> haue boldly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted this haſtie birth of my weake brame to come abroad, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that all curteous Readers will ſhroude it vnder theyr fauourable wings, &amp; ſuffer theſe feare-blaſted
<pb facs="tcp:16349:6"/>fruites to ſhelter vnder the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue ſhaddowes of gentle accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: So bluſhing that this newe ſpoone-feathered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mbrion of my rude Inuention, hath ſo ſoone paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the limits of immodeſtie, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſiring you to pardon my too raſh audacitie, I take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:16349:7"/>
            <head>Ad Lectorem.</head>
            <l>FAelices animae paſcuntur ſemine verbi,</l>
            <l>Ambroſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> comedunt, nectare deinde potant.</l>
            <l>Hic gratia ſluvij ſpatioſo vortice ſtillant,</l>
            <l>Et vita pleno gurgite currit aqua.</l>
            <l>Si ſitis? mimergas fauces in flumine ſacro.</l>
            <l>I ſeris? inuenias ferula lauta Iouis.</l>
            <l>Ad hanc te menſam voco, caena parata,</l>
            <l>Tantum dicenda est gratia, gratis habes.</l>
            <l>Tu gratus conuiua Deo, gratioſus et ille,</l>
            <l>Qui te commuam reddidit angelicum.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16349:7"/>
                  <head>The food of the ſoule.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Iohn cap. 6. verſe 35.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>I am the bread of life, he that commeth to me shall not hunger, and hee that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieueth in me, shall neuer thirſt.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>WHen our Sauiour Chriſt had performed that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly miracle in feeding fiue thouſand men with fiue loues, and two fiſhes, the people which were ſatisfied with that gratis cheer, did followe him to the Citty Caper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naum. But when Ieſus perceiued theyr hypocriſie, that they were fleſhly and carnall hearers, and as a good Writer ſaith, <hi>Paraſiti qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na conglutinat,</hi> hypocrites and bellie Gods, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the trencher doth make friendes to Chriſt: like vnto him
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16349:8"/>which when he ſweat ouer his tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, yet cryed out, <hi>O quanta patimur pro amore Christi,</hi> Lorde what ſuffer we for the loue of Chriſt! Ieſus ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore reprehendeth theſe men, ſaying, <hi>Verily, verily I ſay vnto you, yee ſeeke mee not, becauſe yee ſawe the miracles, but becauſe yee cate the loanes and were filled.</hi> Yet they obſtinatly aunſwered him, VVhat miracles haſt thou done? haſt thou commaunded the Sun and the Moone to ſtand ſtill, as Ioſua did? haſt thou reuiued the widdowes ſon as Elias did? haſt thou made yron to ſwim as Eliza did? haſt thou reuiued the dead bones as Ezechiell did? haſt thou been in the VVhales belly with Ionas? or parted the redde ſea with Moſes? Our Fathers did eate Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na in the VVilderneſſe, Moſes gaue them bread from heauen to eate: but marke I pray you how Ieſus did aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere them. <hi>Nay,</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>Moſes gaue you not bread from Heauen, but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16349:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>my Father gyueth you the true Breade from Heauen: For the breade of GOD is hee vvhich commeth downe from Heauen, and giueth life vnto the world: Then ſayde they vnto him, Lorde euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more giue vs this Breade. And Ieſus ſayde, I am the Breade of life, hee that commeth to me, shall not hunger, &amp; he that belieueth in me, shall neuer thirst.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And thus much for the cohaerence, and occaſion of our Sauiour Chriſts wordes: now particularly as they lie in order: firſt who is this Breade? VVhich is Chriſt, <hi>perſona loquens,</hi> ſignified in this word, <hi>I.</hi> Secondly, what is this breade? <hi>It is the breade of life.</hi> Thirdly, the powerfull efficacie, and effect of this bread, declared in theſe wordes, <hi>Hee that commeth to mee shall not hunger, and hee that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieueth in mee, shall neuer thirſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And firſt, vvho is this Breade, which is, Chriſt: <hi>I am the liuing Breade vvhich came downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:16349:9"/>ſaith Chriſt. <hi>Ego ſum panis vitae, et fons aquae viuae.</hi> I am the bread of life, and ſountaine of liuing water: <hi>Omnia nobis eſt Chriſtus</hi> (ſayth Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe) <hi>ſi eſuris, ipſe eſt panis, ſi ſitis, ipſe eſt fons aquae viua, ſi carus es, ipſe eſt lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſi infirmus es, ipſe medicus, ſi mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus, ipſe vita gratiae et gloriae.</hi> Chriſt is all things to vs, if thou beeſt hungry, he is bread, if thou beeſt thirſty, he is the fountaine of liuing water, if thou beeſt blind he is the light, hee is the health of a feauered ſoule, light of thy life, life of thy deſire, heauen of the minde, guide to thy wandring feete, ſuccorer in necesſity, helper in aduerſitie: yea hee is all things to thee: <hi>I am the liuing bread,</hi> ſayth Chriſt. <hi>The bread which I giue is my flesh, and the drinke which I giue is my blood, my flesh is meate indeede, and my blood is drinke indeede. Hee that ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth my flesh &amp; drinketh my blood, hath eternall life, and I will raiſe him vp
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16349:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>at the latter day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O bleſſed meate, O celeſtiall food: O heauenly Manna: it farre excelleth the Poets Ambroſia: would to God that all of vs daily might eate of this Manna: would to God that all of vs which trauell in the Wilderneſſe of this world, might lodge at ſuch an Inne, where God the father is the hoſt, the holy Ghoſt, the hoſteſſe, the Church the Inne, the croſſe the ſigne, and Chriſt the meate, and drinke. Ariſtotell muſt dine when it pleaſeth Phillip, but heere thou maiſt haue ſtore of ſpirituall foode for the repaſt of thy ſoule, and take it when it pleaſe thy ſelfe. Say but thy grace before this bleſſed banquet, and then ſit downe and ſatisfie thy hunger. The more thou eateſt, the more it encreaſeth, like to Iupiters nectar, the more it is drunke of, the more it ouerfloweth. Neither needſt thou vſe, the counſaile of Lyſander, which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16349:10"/>hee perſcribed to his Daughters, to drinke with a drop of wine a ſpunful of water. Thou maiſt drinke as much of this pretious wine as thou wilt, neither canſt thou infuſe any mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of water, but of the water of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life. This meate is of the like quality with the ſtone of Thracia, which whoſoeuer findeth, is neuer after troubled, ſo whoſoeuer eateth of this meate, is neuer after grieued: labour therefore to get this meate which endureth to euerlaſting life. No water was ſo good as that which came out of the Rocke, no meate ſo delicate as Manna which came from heauen, no wine ſo wholeſome as that which Chriſt made of water at the marriage of Cana, no oyle ſo pretious as that which the Samaritan had, no robe ſo coſtly, as that which the father gaue to the prodigall ſon, no bread, no foode, no meate ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, as this meate of the ſoule
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16349:10"/>which endureth to euerlaſting life. This meate is water to refreſh vs, and wine to cheare vs, this is bread to ſtrengthen vs, and Manna to nouriſh vs, it is a treaſure to inrich vs, and a pearle to adorne vs, it is a fire to purge vs, and ſalt to pouder vs, it is a trumpet to call vs, and wiſedome to inſtruct vs, it is a way to direct vs, and life to reuine vs, it is a Lanterne to guide vs, and a buckler to ſhield vs, it is phiſicke to recure vs, and a ſalue to heale vs: if wee haue this meate, this Manna, this bread, we ſhall haue no neede of Elizens to increaſe our oyle, no neede to begge at the glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons gate, or to ſend vnto Naball the churle for foode: if wee haue this treaſure, wee ſhall not neede to rob the Egiptians, if we haue this pearle, we ſhall not neede the golde of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire, if we haue this water, wee neede not drawe water at Iacobs well, Naaman needes not waſh his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16349:11"/>feete ſeauen times in Iordan, the ſicke needes not to goe to the poole of Betheſda: for this pretious meate, and ineſtimable Manna will purge vs from all leproſie of ſinne: So that we ſhall loath to drinke of the ſlumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cup, of the deuills ſorceries to bewitch vs to ſinne: this bread is Homers <hi>Moly,</hi> and Plinies <hi>Centauria</hi> againſt all luſtfull inchauntments: for this bread, this ſpirituall foode, will ſo clenſe our mindes, and purifie our harts, that we will alwaies deteſt the eye-pleaſing baits of carnall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and wholly delight our ſelues with this ineſtimable treaſure: car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall voluptuouſnes is tranſitorie and fading; the minuts that lackey at the heeles of time runne not faſter away, then doe thoſe pleaſures: but this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall foode, this breade of life, is not like palate-pleaſing dainties, whoſe ſugered ſweeteneſſe once rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht is preſently gone, but it yieldeth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16349:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>the hungry ſoule an euerlaſting frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of moſt rauiſhing pleaſantneſſe: labour therfore for this bread which bringeth to euerlaſting life.</p>
                  <p>The Bees doe labour to get a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle hony:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mella ſtipant et dulci diſtendunt nectare cellas.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But this bread is ſweeter then ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, or the hony-combe. Our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers did eate of the Acorns of the Oakes, and thought them pleaſant meate. And we which by Ceres huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifrie haue learned to bury the reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing graine, doe thinke that Bread moſt delicate foode. O fooliſh Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, let vs rather learne to bury in our harts this reuiuing graine, that in this generall famine of true Chriſtian foode, we may with Ioſeph prouide aboundance of this bread of life, for the benefit of our ſoules: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould we not haue ſuch ſpirituall penurie, and dearth of religion, if our hearts
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16349:12"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:16349:12"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:16349:13"/>were made fertill to bring forth the ſeedes of our ſoules nouriſhment and ſuſtenance. Labor not therefore for the bread that perriſheth, but for this bread which remaineth vnto euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life.</p>
                  <p>Ay but will ſome ſay, where ſhall we find this ſpirituall food, this bread of life? I tell thee Chriſt is this bread of life. Ay but will he perhaps reply: how ſhal I come to Chriſt to get this foode? I bidde thee goe to the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, (Chriſts treaſury) where thou ſhalt finde this Manna, this Bread of life, there is plentifull ſtore, take and ſatisfie thy ſelfe; neyther needſt thou goe farre to ſeeke it, as Dauid did the Arke of GOD, or as Ioſias did the Booke of the Lawe; Neither canſt thou deſire with the Glutton, that one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead might ariſe to teach thee how to finde this bread of life: for now adayes (thanks be giuen to GOD for it) the diſpencers of this
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16349:13"/>bread of life be plentifull, who may without feare or perril ſhew thee the compendious way to ſeek this bread of life. Now Obadia neede not feare Queene Iezabell, to bide an hundred Prophets in a Caue. Moſes need not feare King Pharao, and ſay, I haue a ſtuttering tongue: Ieremy need not feare the Iewes, and ſay, I am a child: for now the Miniſters of Gods word are maintained, and preſerued, and may freely without danger, &amp; boldly without feare, diſpence of this bread of life. Yea &amp; enery one of Chriſtes faithful children, although he be not an heade in the miſticall body of Chriſt, or an eye, or a legge, yea if he be but an hand, yet he may gather of this bread of life, if he be but an eare he may heare of this bread of life, or a tongue, he may praiſe this bread of life, or a mouth, he may receiue this bread of life. Labour therefore for this bread which endureth to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16349:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>life: <hi>I am the Breade of lyfe:</hi> O Ieſus art thou the bread which giueſt life? Thou art a guide to our waies, a gardian to our perſons, a counſeller in our doubts, a comforter in miſery, a patron in neceſsity, and wilt thou be bread alſo? Thou art our keeper, our ſheepheard, our defender, our Sauiour, &amp; wilt thou be bread alſo? O Ieſus, thou art light vnto our eies, muſick to our eares, contentment to our ſoules, &amp; wilt thou be bread alſo? O louing Ieſus, O mercifull redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, O bleſſed Emanuell, O Ieſu, we giue thee our bodies, our ſoules, our ſubſtance, our wealth, our honor, our friends, our Children, our life, and all that is ours: Ieſus wee are not our own but thine, claime vs as thy right, keepe vs as thy charge, loue vs as thy children: Ieſus fight for vs when ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than commeth, heale vs if he woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, reuiue vs if hee killeth, receiue vs if we flie into thy merciful boſom:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16349:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>protect vs when he approcheth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect vs when he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth: Ieſus thou art our foode in the day, thou ſhalt alſo be our repoſe in the night: Ieſus make vs pliable to thy will, reſigned wholy to thy pleaſure. Ieſus forſake vs not leaſt wee perriſh, leaue vs not leaſt we bee ouercome: Ieſus direct our intentions, correct our follies, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our cogitations, protect our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuors: Ieſus grant vs ſorrow for our ſinnes, feare for thy iudgements, loue of thy mercies, thankfulneſſe for this bread of life: <hi>I am the breade of life,</hi> that is, I am the bread of an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall &amp; heauenly life, not of this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and earthly life: for elſe Chriſt might rather haue ſaide, I am the bread of death, and not of life; for this life is a liuing death, and a dying life. But Chriſt is not bread of ſuch a life. But, he is the bread of an immortall, and neuer fading life.</p>
                  <p>Happy therefore is hee which is at
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16349:15"/>this hanquet, &amp; taſteth of this breade of life: Neither is this an imaginarie fruition, or a painted banquet, reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the hungry cheere, which the birds had that fedde themſelues with Zeuxis painted grapes, vntill with picking at ſhaddowes they waxt ſo leane, that they were glad with E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſops Cocke to ſcrape for a Barley corne. But with this bread of life thy foule ſhall be ſo cherriſhed, with this Manna thou ſhalt be ſo wonderfully delighted, that euer after thou ſhalt loath the fleſh pots of Egipt. <hi>Hic pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis eſt corpus meum,</hi> this bread is my body, and therefore thou canſt not miſlike it. O you Miniſters, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſpencers of this hallowed bread of life, feede duly Chriſts flock with this bread of life. Chriſt ſaid to Peter <hi>Paſce, paſce, paſce, feede, feede, feede:</hi> Feede with this bread of life, vvith your doctrine, with your almes: Feede firſt with this bread of life, for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16349:15"/>it is the bread of ſaluation: Secondly feed with your wholſome doctrine, that Chriſts ſheep do not ſurfet with vice, and ſo neede the corſiue of his correction to amend them. Thirdly, feede with almes: but what ſhall I preſſe you to that? Nay I muſt in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſpare you, for the caſe nowe ſo ſtands, that you are liker to liue of almes, then bee able to giue almes: and therfore till happier times come, wherein your diuine function may more bounteouſly be rewarded, I will ſpare you for that poynt, for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie hath no law. In meane while feede with this bread of life, &amp; ſpend your breath happily in the fires of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, crying alarum ſpiritual gainſt ſoule vice, and all wickedneſſe: ſo at laſt you hauing not defrauded Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes children of this bread of life, may haue a moſt bountifull remuneration for your painfull labours, and enioy all heauenly happineſſe, and celeſtiall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16349:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>ioyes, taſting this bread of life, which is prepared for all Gods faithful chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: And thus much ſhall ſuffice to haue ſpoken of the firſt parcell of my text, <hi>I am the bread of life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nowe it followeth that I ſhould briefly ſpeake of the powerfull effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and effect of this bread of life. VVhich by the tongues of Angels cannot be ſo wel declared, as by theſe our Sauiours words, <hi>He that commeth to me shall not hunger, and hee that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieueth in me shall neuer thirſt.</hi> After a man hath taſted of all manner of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate meats, yea although hee hath carouſed new grapes in Alexanders cup, and plentifully payd that dailie Tribute to the ſtomacke, which the lawe of our nature exacteth, yet that foode will not ſatiate him for euer, ſo that hee ſhall neuer hunger, or thirſt after. But this bread, this breade of life hath another power, and effect, for he that eateth of this breade, ſhall
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16349:16"/>neuer hunger, or thirſt more.</p>
                  <p>VVe read in the fourth chapter of Mathewe, that man liueth not by bread onely: but I ſay, man onely li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth by this bread: for this bread is the bread of heauen, which giueth life vnto the world. Therefore be carefull to ſeeke for this breade, for Chriſt doth not forbid vs to ſeeke for this bread: hee ſaith in Mathew the ſixt chapter; Bee not carefull what you ſhal eate, or what you ſhal drink, behold the fowles of heauen, they ſow not, neither reape, nor carry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theyr barnes, yet your heauenly Father feedeth them: the Lillies doe not labour nor ſpin, yet Salomon in all his glory, was not arrayed like one of theſe: therefore take no thought, ſaying, what ſhall wee eate, or what ſhall we drinke, or how ſhall we bee claothed? but ſeeke yee the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, and all theſe things ſhall bee miniſtred vnto you: yet in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16349:17"/>all theſe exemplified admonitions of our Sauiour Chriſt, he doth not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne vs to bee careleſſe for ſeeking of this bread of life: will Chriſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid vs to ſeeke himſelfe? Chriſt is this bread of life, feede on his fleſh, and nouriſh your ſoules: hee is the oyle, and lampe, with which the fiue Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines entered into the Bridgromes chamber. He is the Lord of life, the way of life, the bread of life.</p>
                  <p>Belieue in this Lord, come vnto this way, eate of this bread, you ſhall neuer hunger, or thirſt after. But ſome man peraduenture may obiect, can bread extinguiſh hunger, and thirſt? When a man is dry and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, he doth not vſe to eate bread: I aunſwere, that the Hebrewes doe vſe this phraſe, <hi>panem comedere, pro caenare,</hi> for to ſup, as Maiſter Caluin heere well noteth: ſo wee ſay in the Lords prayer, <hi>danobis quotidianum pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> giue vs our daily bread, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16349:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>all neceſſary things belonging to a man; eate of this bread of life, and you ſhall not neede to ſay, giue vs our daily breade, for you ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hunger, or thirſt after: <hi>Hee that commeth to mee, shall not hunger: accedat ad Chriſtum omnis anima:</hi> let euery ſoule come to Chriſt, and hee will refreſh it: I will (ſaith he) feede the hungry ſoule, and refreſh all faint harts. I am the ſtrength of the feeble, the ſuccor of the hungry, a refuge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt euill weather, a ſhadow againſt heate: I am a continuall feaſt, where all hungry &amp; languiſhing ſoules may ſatisfie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with celeſtiall food. O well are they, and happy ſhall they be, which ſit at this heauenly Table, and eate of this bleſſed, and ſpirituall meate, the price and redemptian of theyr ſoules. Heere is Manna which the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael ſhal neuer lothe: the wiſe Ethnick mans ſaying vpon a feaſt, heere taketh no place: <hi>Prima
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16349:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>cratera</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ad ſitim pertinet, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunda ad hilaritatem, tertia ad volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, quarta ad inſaniam:</hi> The firſt cuppe belongeth to thirſt, the ſecond to mirth, the third to pleaſure, and the fourth to inſobrietie. But at this feaſt of the Soule, it is quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for the more thou drinkeſt, <hi>tanto propriores ad animae ſanitatem, et ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem:</hi> thou art ſo much the neerer to the health, and welfare of thy ſoule. Caliſtenes ſaid to Alexander, that he had rather carouſe olde graines with Diogenes in his diſh, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> new grapes with Alexander in his cup, for of all the Gods (quoth hee) I loue not Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culapius. But whoſoeuer drinketh in this cup, ſhall not neede Aeſculapius phiſicke, for it is a preſent remedy, &amp; a ſoueraigne reſtoratiue againſt the maladies of a ſinfull ſoule: it is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent potion, and a moſt wholſome purgation to expell the leproſie of a ſinne-ſeauered ſoule.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16349:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  </p>
                  <p>The precious ſtone Sandaſtra hath nothing in outward appearance, but being broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it poureth forth beams, like the ſun: ſo this bread of life hath not an outward glea of ſuperexcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent goodnes, but taſte it, and then it poureth forth ſuch admirable excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, that thou ſhalt neuer hunger any more. Therfore the ſheepheards of Chriſtes flock, ſhould onely feede his lambes with this bread of life.</p>
                  <p>VVhen they bee hungry, they ſhould fill them with this Breade of life. They ſhould cry vnto them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, Come vnto Chriſt, and he wil giue you the bread of life, ſo that you ſhall neuer hunger or thirſt any more. The Miniſters ſhould haue a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall cry, not like the Swallows, which haue <hi>matutinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cantum,</hi> a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſong, or as the Graſhoppers, <hi>meridianum cantum,</hi> a noone ſong, or as the Owles, <hi>veſpertinum cantum,</hi> an euening ſong, or as the Cocks, <hi>ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucanum
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16349:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>cantum,</hi> a ſong before mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but they ſhold haue a morning ſong, a noone ſong, an euening ſong, and a ſong before day light, to awake Chriſtes ſlumbering ſheepe to come vnto Chriſt, and eate of this bread of life, ſo they ſhal neuer hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger or thirſt more. <hi>He that commeth to me shall not hunger, &amp; he that belieueth in me, shall neuer thirst.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To belieue in Chriſt, is the totall ſumme of all Chriſtian religion: For our fayth in the death, and paſsion of our Lord, and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, is the ſure foundation of our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Fides in Christo</hi> (ſaith S. Ierome) <hi>est fundamentum humanae ſaluationis:</hi> Faith in Chriſt is the foundation of mans ſaluation: without this fayth, all our vertuous actions, &amp; good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours, be in vaine. So ſaith S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine, <hi>Sine fide falſa est omnis virtus,</hi> without faith, all vertue is in vaine: <hi>Sine fide impoſsibile eſt placere Deo,</hi> with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16349:19"/>out faith it is imposſible to pleaſe God: <hi>Sine fide omnis labor vacuuo.</hi> VVithout faith all our labour is fruſtrate. Faith is the porter of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen gate, and not Saint Peter.</p>
                  <p>He that hath faith, yea but as much as a graine of muſtard ſeede, ſhall be able to remooue Mountaines: VVherefore let vs labour to get this faith, which being obtained, we ſhal not neede any other treaſury: let vs lay vp this iewell in our harts, which will inrich vs euer after. The Anoto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts ſay, that in the heart of a man, there is a little whole, which hath nothing in it. VVhereupon a good writer ſayth, that this little Cabinet and Cell of the heart, God doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue for himſelfe, to be a chamber, and a priuate manſion for him to dwell, &amp; keepe therin: let vs therfore beſtow vpon our gracious Lord this pretious gemme, this excellent orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to adorne, and beautifie this
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16349:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>inward chamber. That when it ſhall pleaſe the Lord to call vs to the high ſtarre-chamber ouer our heades, hee may <hi>Antipelargein,</hi> that is, requite vs with farre more ſumptuous iewells, and richer ornaments, making vs co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitors with Angells, and the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red paragons of all perfection: let vs therefore confidently belieue in Chriſt, deſiting him moſt heartily, and vnfainedly, to giue vs of this breade of life, which is the only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoratiue againſt hunger, and thirſt. Auicen like a foole ſayd in his Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſmes, that golde was the beſt reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue. No, no, this bread of life, is the moſt heauenly remedie againſt al diſeaſes: it is a poyſon for vice, but a life-giuing potion for vertue. It is the bread of death for carnall gluttonie, but it is the bread of life for ſpirituall hunger. If thou beeſt famiſhed, eate of this bread, and it will reuiue thee: it can heale all leproſie of ſinne, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16349:20"/>remooue all maladies from a ſin-ſick ſoule: it is the nectar of our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Lethe of our iniquines: taſt but once of this breade of life, &amp; thou ſhalt euer after loath the ſuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red cares, and bewitching damties of luſtfull affections: looke daily vppon this bread of life, and thou ſhalt euer after hide thine eyes, and ſtop thine eares, which are now captiued vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes to behold, and heare the leger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demaine of humaine iugling deſires: all ſiren ſonges of carnall concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and vices loue-lines, which now are imprinted in thy breſt, ſhall be quight cancelled out, after thou haſt once digeſted inwardly, and thy ſoule hath had an happy concoction of this bread of life: it purgeth all the hidden corruption of mans folly, &amp; giueth working pills to vomit vp ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall tranſgresſions: it is the preſent remedie for a body, which lieth in a conſumption of grace, to taſt of this
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16349:21"/>bread of life, with in a ſhort ſpace by the vnſpeakeable hidden operation, will make a bleſſed recouerie for this languiſhing creature. If thy ſoule bee hungry or thirſty, behold two ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall riuers flowing out of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe of Chriſts body, in the one, thou ſhalt find this bread of life, in the other, this water of life: taſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them, and thou ſhalt neuer hunger, or thirſt more; yea the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of this bread cannot bee ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently declared by the tongue of the worthieſt Orator. VVherefore let vs only ſatisfie our ſoules with this bread of life, whoſe power, and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie our daily Orator Chriſt Ieſus, hath declared vnto vs in theſe words, <hi>Hee that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to me shall not hunger, and he that belieueth in me shall neuer thirſt.</hi> Wherefore to drawe to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, let vs from the bottome of our hearts, deſire Chriſt Ieſus euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more to giue vs of this bread, that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16349:21"/>when the glaſſe of our life is runne out, and with the Phenix wee may diſcerne the terme of our dayes, and with the Swanne diſcouer our fatall end, that it would pleaſe him to feed our hungry ſoules with this ſpirituall foode, this bread of life, and place them at his heauenly table, to ſatisfie themſelues with this celeſtiall ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet: yea whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our breath vaniſheth, our eyes waxe dim, and wee turned out of the houſeroome of this tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory world, repayre vnto our doomeſday houſe, where the wormes (the dead mens lawyers) ſhall take their fees out of vs their graue-clients, and our bodies ſhall be their bread to ſatiate their hunger, yet thou (O Ieſus) would vouchſafe to giue vs thy body, the only breade of life, for to nouriſh our hungry ſoules, that by the winges of a liuely faith wee may fly vp to the heauens, and inioy that age of vnſpeakeable
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16349:22"/>pleaſures: the eternall father through the merrits of his deereſt ſonne, by the ſcepter of his holy ſpirit, ſo rule our hearts, that wee being righteous as Elias, and our prayers feruent as thoſe of Elias, they may peirce the clouds, and open heauen, and thence bring downe this bread of life, this dew of diuine grace vppon vs, and ſatisfie our ſoules with this miſticall banquet of Chriſts body. O Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame our tongues with the zeale of deuotion, that our prayers may bee feruent, and may make a ſweete in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe to pacifie thy wrath, that thou blotting out all our vnworthineſſe out of thy memory, maiſt graciouſly hearken to our petitions, and maiſt grant vs this ineſtimable treaſure, the price, and raunſom of our ſoules re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption: if the Lyons ſeeke their meate of God, if the Oxe knowe his owner, and the Aſſe his maiſters crib, graunt vnto vs a moſt carefull deſire
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16349:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>to craue this meate of our ſoules, and to waite and ſeeke for this bread of life, that we which were created by a conſultation of the Dietie, redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the pretious bloud of Chriſt, ſanctified by the holy Ghoſt, may be partakers of this bleſſed bread of life, and in the end, and without all end, ſit at his heauenly table, raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning together with the Trinity in the Kingdome of heauen, to which bee all glory, power, praiſe, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, both now, and for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16349:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16349:23"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A</hi> SHORT AND neceſsary Treatiſe, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled: <hi>Deaths welcome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>Sa: Garey.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AT LONDON, Printed by I. R. for Ieffery Charleton. 1605.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16349:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16349:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the moſt puiſſant Emperor, and Conquerer of all the vvorld, <hi>Death,</hi> greeting.</head>
                  <p>LIfe (ſaith the Philoſopher) is but a borrowed dreame of pleaſure, a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of delight, a pageant of tranſitory happineſse, and Death is a Harbinger of eternitie, a bringer of felicitie, a Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of glory; it is a pyrat of life, and yet a pilot to life, a conductor to the heauenly hauen of bliſſe, the Angell to keepe Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, wherein none enters but by the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of his fatall ſword. Sith therefore (ô Death) thou art the Groome-porter to let out life, and let in life, the remoouer (as <hi>Aeſchilus</hi> calleth thee) of worldly ſorrows, the deliuerer (as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith) of troubled mindes, the laylor which art content with the fees of our life, to ſet our Soules at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, I heere inuite and welcome thee to the loathſome banquet of my body, fat thy
<pb facs="tcp:16349:25"/>pale cheekes with the cates of my life, and glut thy hungry appetite with my vitall ſpirits, onely doe me this fauour, that I may ſay my Grace at this laſt ſupper, and then ſit downe vpon my dying bed, and drinke vp the ſweet drop of ſower life, and the ſcraps, and dead bones of my body, and carkaſſe of my fleſh take away, and keepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the doomſday houſe, vntil my Soule by the liuely wings of faith, deſcending fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen at the generall reſurrection, be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited one to another, and there enioy an endleſſe age of pleaſures, to the which (ô Death) ſoone bring mee, that I may ſay to the VVorldes miſery, which I ſay to thee, farewell.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your louing, and vntill you come liuing friend,</hi> Sa. Garey.</signed> Tu nil reſcribas, attamen ipſe veni.</closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16349:25"/>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Treatiſe, entituled Deaths welcome.</head>
                  <p>THE principall motiue vvhich doth encourage a man to wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and imbrace death, is the aſſured hope of the future life, and of thoſe ioyes, which hee ſhall enioy in the neuer fading kingdome.</p>
                  <p>Therefore <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſaith, Vnleſſe the dead be raiſed againe, what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantageth it me to haue fought with beaſts at <hi>Epheſus?</hi> For vnleſſe there were a reſurrection of the dead, and an immortall life to be obtained after this our pilgrimage, why ſhould we liue in ieopardy euery howre, &amp; ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſuch perſecution in this world, &amp; not rather follow the rules of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picures, eate, drinke, for to morrow
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16349:26"/>we ſhall die: and vppon our graues, engraue the Epitaph of <hi>Sardanapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> which hee writ a little before his death,</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Cum te mortalem noris, preſentibus exple,</l>
                     <l>Delicijs animu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, post mortem nulla voluptas,</l>
                     <l>Et venere, et plumis, et caenis <hi>Sardanapali.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <p>This I ſay, were the beſt pleaſing life, to eate with the Epicure, ſleepe with <hi>Endimion,</hi> carouſe with <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> &amp; with the rich man in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to flatter our ſelues, ſaying, Soule thou haſt much goods layde vp in ſtore, eate, drinke, and take thy reſt. VVho would endure the mocks and ſcornes of the world, who would be roſted with <hi>Laurentius,</hi> or martyred with the Apoſtles, vnleſſe they ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, that after the veſſel of theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies were ſeaſoned in the wombe of the earth, they ſhould arriue at that bleſſed vndiſcouered country, where is no mediocritie of ioy, no end of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16349:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>pleaſure. So then we Chriſtians, who are illuminated with the bright ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny beames of Chriſts Goſpell, wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect ſuch Epicurian opinions of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Atheiſts, who belieue there is no reſurrection, no crowne of glorie remaining for them after theyr life is ended: but S. <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth vs an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leſſon; For (ſaith he) if the dead be not raiſed, then is Chriſt not riſen, &amp; if Chriſt be not riſen, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our fayth is in vaine. And in another place; If in this life we haue hope onely, then of all men we be moſt miſerable.</p>
                  <p>So <hi>Iob</hi> ſaide, when hee was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with a ſea of ſorrowe; I am certaine that my redeemer liueth, and that I ſhall riſe out of the earth in the latter day, and that I ſhall be clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed againe with this skinne, and ſee GOD in my fleſh, yea I my ſelfe ſhal behold him, not with other, but with theſe ſame eyes.</p>
                  <p>This poynt of religion concerning
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16349:27"/>our reſurrection, the very Heathen VVriters haue approoued, for thus <hi>Cato</hi> ſpeaking to <hi>Scipio</hi> &amp; <hi>Laelius</hi> in <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceros</hi> booke <hi>De ſenectute,</hi> ſaith; Dooſt thou thinke that I would haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken ſo great labors both by day and night, both at home, and at the warre, if my glory ſhould haue had the ſame limits which my life hath? So <hi>Plato</hi> in his Booke <hi>De animae im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalit.</hi> ſaith, That the ſoule of man is immortall, and that it ſhall liue in another world. So <hi>Socrates</hi> when he did drinke the venemous poyſon, with which he ſhould breake of the feeble thred of mortalitie, ſaid: I am ſure that my ſoule ſhall liue, and that my body ſhall ariſe in the ſecond ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer dying birth.</p>
                  <p>But why doe I ſpend my time in a matter ſo needleſſe to be confirmed, ſith the ſcripture (the oracles of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) be ſo plentifull of proues: &amp; all VVriters doe defend this vndeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16349:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>veritie: for who can denie, but that there is a reſurrection, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reſerued for them, which die in the Lord: if that this life were the only Paradiſe where we ſhould take our delights, who would not deſire a long life with <hi>Methuſalah,</hi> or ſtore of wealth with <hi>Salomon,</hi> or honor with <hi>Haman:</hi> but wee that knowe this earth to bee nothing elſe but an element of ſorrowe, this world to be but a Hydra of renewing cares, will not place our eternall affaires, and treaſures of heauen vpon the gliding ſtreame, of this vncertaine life. For we are ſurely perſwaded, that after the houre glaſſe of this momentary life is runne out, we ſhall be impara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dized in heauen, and made free De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizers in that celeſtiall Ieruſalem, whoſe ioyes and praiſes doe ſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound all inhumaine inuention to comprehend: for ſo ſayth Saint <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie;</hi> No man is able to tell how
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16349:28"/>great, the ioyes of the heauenly Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhall be. Becauſe (as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſayth) the diſhes of the heauenly banquet are ſo great, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be meaſured, ſo long that they cannot be limitted, ſo many that they cannot be numbred, and ſo precious, that they cannot bee eſteemed. Yet notwithſtanding, that thoſe ioyes be ineſtimable, and innumerable, we ſhall be certaine to inioy them, after this life is finiſhed. For ſo ſayth Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> when this earthly houſe of this Tabernacle is deſtroyed, wee knowe wee haue a building giuen of God, that is, an houſe not made with hands, but eternall in the heauens: there ſhall wee haue ioyes without meaſure, pleaſures without end. We ſhall (ſayth Saint <hi>Augustine</hi>) ſee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wearineſſe, we ſhall loue with-meaſure, and ſhall giue praiſes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end. Then ſhall <hi>Dauid</hi> taſt how ſweete the Lord is. I am ſure (ſayth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16349:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>hee) I ſhall ſee the goodneſſe of the Lord in the land of the liuing. Theſe ioyes and the hope of the fruition of that bleſſed future life, doth inbol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and harden a true Chriſtian a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his fatall houre, willingly, and ioyfully to leaue this world, (which is <hi>valles miſeriae,</hi> as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth) that hee may ſee the new Ieruſalem, &amp; that bleſſed companie of Angells, whoſe glory, whoſe praiſes, whoſe bleſſedneſſe, whoſe delights, no tongue is able to expreſſe, no heart to conceiue.</p>
                  <p>Yet that I might giue you a taſt of thoſe ioyes, and as it were a ſhaddow of the Sunne ſhine of that glory, which we ſhall poſſeſſe after the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of our earthly bodies, I will recite a few things, which I haue reade in the Scriptures, and in other places concerning the bleſſedneſſe of that happie life: for the ioyes of heauen bee the onely cauſes which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16349:29"/>doe mooue and incite vs, to liue god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this preſent life. For what doth make the laborer to worke, but his hire: The husbandman to toyle but the hope of a good harueſt. The Souldier to fight but the hope of victory, and of obtaining of a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: ſo in like manner, what doth ſtirre vp mortall men to liue religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and louingly to welcome the approach of death, but only the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident hope of that hire, which none of them by vertuall merrits ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue. The hope of that good har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, wherein they ſhall reape all contentment of minde. The hope of that wiſhed victory and precious Garland, wherewith they ſhall bee adorned and floriſh like Angelis. Theſe bee the true motiues and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements, which doe giue alacrity and bold ſpirits, to vndergoe the pangs of death willinly, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and animate all timerous and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16349:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>fleſhly minded perſons, to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted, and theyr eares tickled with muſick in the daunce of death, when they ſhall ſeriouſly conſider, they ſhal paſſe from death to life, from morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to immortality, from miſerie to ioy, from pertill to ſecuritie, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage to libertie, from aduerſitie to proſperitie, and in fine, from hell and damnation, to bliſle and ſaluation. Howbeit, that I may giue ſome kind of ſauour and feeling knowledge thereof, which may allure fearefull men cheerefully to expect, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to ſuffer the Iayler Death to lock vp the windowes of the priſon houſe of theyr ſoules, I intend heere to rehearſe euen worde for worde, what <hi>S. Augustine</hi> ſaith in one of his Meditations, namelie, the 22 medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, ſpeaking of the felicitie of the future life.</p>
                  <p>O life (ſayth hee) prepared by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God for his friends, a bleſſed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16349:30"/>life, a ſeeure life, a quiet life, a beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, a cleane life, a chaſt life, a holy life, a life that knoweth no death, a life without ſadnes, without labour, without griefe, without trouble, without corruption, without feare, without varietie, without alteration, a life repleniſhed with all beautie, and dignitie, where there is neither enemie that can offend, or delight that can annoy, where loue is prefect, and no feare at all, where the day is euerlaſting, &amp; the ſpirit of all is one, where almightie God is ſeene face to face, who is the onely meate where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon they feede without any loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe. It delighteth me to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy brightneſſe, &amp; thy treaſures do reioyce my lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging hart; the more I conſider thee, the more I loue thee. The great deſire I haue of thee, doth wonderfully delight mee, and no leſſe pleaſure is it vnto mee to keepe thee in my remembrance. O
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16349:30"/>life moſt happy: O Kingdome truly bleſſed, where there is no death, no end, neither yet ſuccesſion of time, where the day continueth euermore without night, knoweth no mutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where the victorious conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, beeing ioyned with thoſe euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting quieres of Angels, and hauing his head crowned with a Garland of glory, ſingeth vnto almighty godone of the ſonges of Syon. O happy, yea &amp; moſt happy ſhould my ſoule bee, if when the race of this my pilgrimage is ended, I might bee worthy to ſee thy glory, thy bleſſednes, thy beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, thy walls, and gates of thy Citty, thy ſtreetes, thy lodgings, thy noble Cittizens, and thine omnipotent King, in his moſt glorious Maieſtie. The ſtones of thy walls, are precious, thy gates are adorned with bright pearles, thy ſtreetes are of very fine gold, in which there neuer faile per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall praiſes. Thy houſes are paued
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16349:31"/>with rich ſtones, wrought with Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phires, and couered aboue with masſie gold: where none entereth that is not cleane, neither doth any abide there, that is defiled.</p>
                  <p>Faire and beautifull in thy delights, art thou O Ieruſalem our mother: none of thoſe things are ſuffered in thee, that are ſuffered heere. There is great diuerſitie betweene thy things, and the things that we doe continually ſee in this miſerable life. In thee is neuer ſeene darkeneſſe, nor any change of time. The light that ſhineth in thee, commeth neither of Iampes, nor of the Moone, nor yet of the bright gliſtering Starres. But God that proceedeth of God, and the light that commeth of light, is he that gieueth clearenſſe vnto thee. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the very King of Kings him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, keepeth continuall reſidence in the midſt of thee, compaſſed about with his officers and ſeruants. There
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16349:31"/>doe the Angels in their orders, and quiers ſing a moſt ſweete and melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Harmonie: There is celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a perpetuall feaſt, with euery one of them that commeth thether, after his departure out of this his pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. There be the orders of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; there is the famous ſociety of Apoſtles: there is the inuicible army of Martirs; there is the moſt reuerend aſſembly of Confeſſors, there be the true religious perſons. There are the holy Virgines, which haue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the pleaſures of the world, and the frailty of the fleſh: there bee the young men &amp; women, more aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in vertue, then in yeares: there are the ſheepe, and little lambes, that haue eſcaped from the wolues, and from the deceitfull ſnares of this life. There charity raigneth in her full perfection. O happy were I, yea and very happy indeede, if at what time I ſhall bee looſed out of the priſon of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16349:32"/>this wretched bodie, I might bee thought worthy to heare thoſe ſongs of that heauenly melodie, ſung in the praiſes of the euerlaſting King, by all the Cittizens of that ſo noble Citty: Happy were I, yea and very happy, if I might obtaine a roome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Chaplens of that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and waite for my turne alſo to ſing my <hi>Alleluia:</hi> if I might bee neare vnto my King, my God, my Lord, &amp; ſee him in his glory, euen as he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed mee, when he ſayd, <hi>Iohn,</hi> 17. O father this is my laſt determinate will, that all thoſe, that thou haſt giuen vnto me, may bee with mee, and ſee the glory which I had with thee before the world was created. Hetherto are the words of Saint <hi>Auguſtine:</hi> Marke alſo I pray you, how Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> deſcribeth in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation the new Ieruſalem, xxi. And I <hi>Iohn</hi> (ſayth he) ſaw a new heauen, and a new earth, for the firſt heauen
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16349:32"/>and the firſt earth were paſſed away, and there was no more Sea; and I <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw the holy Citty new Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, come downe from God out of heauen, prepared as a bride trimmed for her husband; and I heard a great voyce out of heauen ſaying, behold, the Tabernacle of God is with men, and hee will dwell with them, and they ſhall bee his people, and God himſelfe ſhall bee their God with them. And God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes, and there ſhal be no more death, neither ſorrowe, neither crying, neither ſhal there bee any more paine. For the firſt thinges are paſſed: and there came vnto mee an Angell, ſaying, come, I will ſhow thee the Bridegroome the lambs wife. And he carried me away to an hie mountaine, and ſhowed me that great Cittie, that holy Ieruſalem, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending out of heauen from God, hauing the glory of God, and her
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16349:33"/>ſhining was like vnto a ſtone moſt precious, as a Iaſper ſtone as cleere as Chriſtall, and had a great wall and hie, and had twelue gates, and at the gates twelue Angels, and the names written, which are the twelue tribes of the children of Iſraell; and the building of the wall of it was of Iaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and the Citty was pure gold, like vnto cleare glaſſe; the foundation of the wall of the Cittie, was garniſhed with all manner of precious ſtones; and the twelue Gates were twelue pearles, and euery gate is of one pearle, and the ſtreetes of the Citty is pure gold, as ſhining glaſſe: and there is no Temple, for the Lord al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, &amp; the Lambe are the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of it. There is the pure Riuer of water of life, cleare as Chriſtall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding out of the Throne of God, and of the Lambe. There is the tree of life, which beare twelue manner of fruites. There is no night, no can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16349:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>or light of the Sun, for the Lord God giueth them light, and they ſhal ſhine for euermore.</p>
                  <p>Now then tell me (ô zealous Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian) what needeſt thou feare death, ſith fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a moſt miſerable world, thou ſhalt paſſe to a glorious kingdome, from miſeries to euelaſting ioyes, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> labours &amp; troubles, to eternally plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and delights. Will not the hope of theſe rewards mooue thee to wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Death? The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heare ſome more ioyes, which thou ſhalt poſſeſſe in the bleſſed future life.</p>
                  <p>The righteous ſhall ſhine as the Sunne in the kingdome of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; They ſhall haue the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of euerlaſting life; They ſhall be as the Angels of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; they ſhall be in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome; they ſhal be where Chriſt is, and ſee his glorie.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, The eye hath not ſeene, the eare hath not heard, nor hath it entered into the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16349:34"/>hart of man, the thinges which God hath prepared for them which loue him; vve ſhall be with the Lord, and liue with him for euer; vvee ſhall be veſſels vnto honour; vvee ſhal haue the crowne of righteouſnes; we ſhal dwel in the Citty of the liuing God, the heauenly Ieruſalem, and ſee the innumerable company of Angels.</p>
                  <p>VVhen Chriſt our chiefe Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard ſhal appeare (ſaith S. <hi>Peter</hi>) we ſhal receiue an incorruptible crowne of glory; and S. <hi>Iohn</hi> in his Reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſaith; To him that ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth. I will giue to eate of the Tree of life, which is in the midſt of the Paradice of almightie GOD; The righteous ſhal neither hunger nor thirſt, heate nor ſunne ſhall not hurt them: for he that fauoureth them, shal lead them, and giue them drinke of the ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wells: they ſhal eate, drinke, and be merry for very quietnes of hart: yea, their gladnes and theyr ioy ſhall
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16349:34"/>continue for euer and euer.</p>
                  <p>The wiſe (ſaith <hi>Daniell</hi>) ſhall gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter as the ſhining of heauen, and be like the ſtarres worlde without end. My people (ſaith God) ſhal dwell in pleaſant peace, and ſafe holds, &amp; shal haue continuall reſt without diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance.</p>
                  <p>Therefore when the Pſalmograph did conſider the excellent things that are ſpoken of the Citty of God, and of the great Citty holy <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> he cryed out, O how amiable are thy dwellings (thou Lorde of Hoſts) my ſoule hath a deſire &amp; longing to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Courts of the Lord. My hart &amp; my fleſh reioyce in the liuing God: for who can be delighted with the kennell of this life, when he ſhall read what the diuine Egle, the Egle of Diuines hath ſpoken of this cittie, that it is pure golde like vnto cleare glaſſe: that the ſtreets are pure golde as ſhining glaſſe: that the ſhining is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16349:35"/>like vnto a ſtone moſt precious, as a Iaſper ſtone, cleere as Chriſtall: that the foundations of the wall are gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with all manner of precious ſtones: that the twelue gates bee 12. pearles: that the keepers of the 12. gates be 12. Angels: that the light is the gloty of God, &amp; the lambe: that the temple is the Lord God almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and the lambe: that the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants be pure, and that no vncleane thing entereth therein: that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords be the booke of Life: that the water is a water of Life: that the tree is a tree of Life: and of the mimuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Cittizens, that there ſhall be no more curſe, no night, no need of candle, nor light of Sun: and that the eſtate of the Cittizens is this, that they ſhall raigne for euermore. Oh who would not willingly diue into the whitlpoole of deuouring Death, and deſire that the twiſted feeble threds of our life would euery houre
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16349:35"/>vntwine, ſo that we might be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into this heauenly foeietie, after the ioyfull diuorcement of Soule &amp; bodie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Balaam</hi> wiſhed, that his ſoule might die the death of the righteous, and that his laſt end might bee like vnto theirs: &amp; the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> wiſhed rather to bee a doore keeper in the houſe of God, then to dwell in the tents of the vngodly; one day in thy Courts is better then a thouſand: &amp; bleſſed are they that dwell in thy houſe, they will alwaies be prayſing of thee.</p>
                  <p>Theſe ioyes might allure vs to raiſe our thoughts, aboue the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie leuell of this world, and to ſay with <hi>Poule,</hi> I deſire to be looſed from this body of ſinne, and to bee with Chriſt; no muſicke ſhould bee ſo ſweete vnto our eares, as the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of death; for death is our faithful conductor to this Ieruſalem:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16349:36"/>I haue oft wondered at the folly of our nature, which doe ſo abhorre to heare the mention of our death; yea euen aged men whoſe ſpring was paſt, whoſe ſummer ſpent, and euen arriued at the fall of the leafe, and winter cullours had ſtayned their hoary head, whoſe tired ſhip did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to leake and grate vppon the grauell of their graue, yet how timer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly they were amazed, when they perceiued, that the trumpet of death beganne to giue his laſt ſound. O fooliſh imbecillitie, who would not willingly bee luiled in deaths ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering fits, and cloſe vp the day of his life, that from a mortall day hee may come to an euerlaſting morrow. It is they will ſay themſelues, the greateſt delight and pleaſure in this world, to heare the Nightingales re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count their tunes with daintie varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: to ſee Valleis compaſſed about with ſiluer Riuers. To ſee medowes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16349:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>enameled with eye pleaſing flowers; to ſee Gardens bedecked with roſes and lillies, and pleaſant ſhades. Or to heare the Lambs craue their Dams comfort, with their bleting oratorie, yet theſe be trifles: from heauen you ſhall heare the Angells ſinging <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luia,</hi> which will ſurpaſſe the muſicke of Nightingalls: there is the Eden of content: the Paradiſe of pleaſure. Will you haue paſtures to paſtime in: Marke what Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſaith, <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma electorum ſunt vultus Dei, vbi erit perpetua latitia et ſecuritas:</hi> Doſt thou delight in ſhepheard &amp; Lambs? there is our watchfull ſhepheard Chriſt, &amp; there is the Lambe of God, crauing day and night for the comfort of our ſoules: yet I will ſaile a little further into the broad Sea of theſe celeſtiall ioyes. It will bee no ſmall ioye vnto vs, when our ſoules ſhall bee preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before the Throne of the moſt bleſſed Trinitie, by the hands of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16349:37"/>Angells, and they placing them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Tribunall ſeate of almightie God, ſhall declare our good workes, our almes deedes, our prayers, our faſtings, our innocencie of life, our temperance in diet, our croſſes, our tribulations, torments, iniuries, and afflictions we haue ſuffered for Gods ſake. Saint <hi>Luke</hi> writeth that when holy Tabitha, the great almes giuer was dead, all the widdowes and poore people came about the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> ſhowing him the coates, and garments ſhe had giuen them, wherewith the Apoſtle being mooued, made his prayer to almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, for that ſo mercifull a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and by his prayers he raiſed her againe to life. Now what a ioy and gladneſſe will it be to vs, when the Angells ſhall rehearſe our ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and good deedes, which wee haue performed in our liſe. Then ſhall wee fully perceiue the value of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16349:37"/>vertue; there the obedient man ſhall talke of victories; there ſhall the Kings come loaden with the ſpoiles of honor. There ſhall the valiant men enter with triumphe, which haue conquered ſathan and all his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes. There ſhall the innocent Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines enter, which haue liued chaſtly in the world, adorned with Garlands of Lillies and Roſes; There ſhall the whole Court of heauen imbrace with kiſſes religious biſhops, which haue beene watchfull ſhepheards o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the whole flocke of Chriſt: There ſhal the conſtant Martirs bee receiued, which haue ſuffered mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirdome for the Goſpell; There ſhal the aged men enter, which haue with diſcretion and wiſedome paſſed their daies on earth; There ſhall the vertuous young men receiue there reward: There vertue ſhal be hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red according to her merrit. Oh how ſweete and ſauorie ſhall the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16349:38"/>fruite of vertue then bee. Sweet is the fountaine to the weary traueller, ſweete is reſt to the tyred ſeruaunt, ſweet is the cold euening after a hote ſunny day; yet much more ſweeter will it be to the faithfull ſeruaunts of almightie GOD, and Saints of the heauenly Cittie, to haue peace after warre, continuall quietneſſe after paynes, ioy after trouble, ſecuritie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter danger.</p>
                  <p>Then ſhal not the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael neede to feare <hi>Pharao.</hi> Then <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docheus</hi> neede not feare proude am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious <hi>Haman.</hi> Then <hi>Ioſephs</hi> feete ſhal not be pinched and hurt in the ſtocks.</p>
                  <p>Then the VViddowe of <hi>Sarep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi> may caſt away her cruſe and her meale, for ſhee ſhal be ſatisfied vvith heauenly manna. Then may the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Father Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> take his reſt, who in his watchings made no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene dayes and nights,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16349:38"/>beating his breaſt in his deuour pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and fighting againſt the violence of the old ſerpent.</p>
                  <p>Then <hi>Ieremy</hi> need not renew his tragicall note in his prophecie, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; O that my head were a well of vvater, and my eye-lidds fountaines of teares, that I might weepe day &amp; night for the ſlaine of the Dangliters of my people.</p>
                  <p>Then may the ſtout harted Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers lay downe theyr ſwords and ſpears, for there is a region of peace, and a place of tranquilitie: for euery one in that Cittie, enioy the fruite of ſweet peace.</p>
                  <p>That Citty is ſituated aboue all the Elements, where no cloudes can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, no ſtormy winds can blow, no tempetuous waues can come. There is the lambe of God Chriſt Ieſus, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing his deere ſpouſe the Church, ſaying, My ſiſter, my ſpouſe, how fayre &amp; how pleaſant art thou, ô my
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16349:39"/>Loue in pleaſures: thy lippes (my ſpouſe) drop as honny combes. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and milke is vnder thy tongue: my ſpouſe is as a Garden encloſed with Roſes and Lillies, ô Paradiſe of Gardens, ô well of liuing waters, ô my vvel-beloued, thou art the faireſt among women. O ioyfull time, when we ſhall ſee face to face Chriſt Ieſus, and heare the ſweet communication betweene him and the Church his beloued Spouſe.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſed are they (ſaith holy <hi>Tobias</hi>) that loue thee, and enioy thy peace. VVherefore <hi>Bernard</hi> might well ſay, If any man ſhould taſt in his heart, howe great the pleaſantneſſe of the heauenly reward is, then euery thing in the earth will ſeeme bitter, euerie comly thing ſhamefull, and all ioy ſorrowfulnes. Alſo in another place he ſaith, In compariſon of heauenly ioy, all pleaſure is griefe, all delights ſorrow, all ſweetnes bitterneſſe, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16349:39"/>all honor horribleneſſe. VVherfore I will exhort all godly Chriſtians, with the graue ſentence of bleſſed S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> where he ſaith, O man be feruent in the loue &amp; deſire of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, where euery action is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out labor, reſt without idlenes, praiſe without diſdaine, life without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; where there is no want, but all ſuperfluitie, where there is no good hidden, and no euill preſent.</p>
                  <p>Oh into what an Ocean of ioyes my ioyfull tongue leades me, my eyes waxe dim at the ſunne-ſhine of this glory, my penne begins to tyre, and yet I will not like a badde Hiſtorian, ſpeake of the meaneſt ioyet, and cut of the courſe of the greateſt happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Therefore my tongue, mine eyes, my penne, each of them ſhall ſing a part to make vp the harmonie of this exceſsiue felicitie. It is an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable pleaſure to a chriſtian whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhall arriue at this bleſſed hauen, &amp;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16349:40"/>ſhall turne back, and looke vpon the courſe of his nauigation, wherein he hath ſailed in the tempeſtuous ſea of his former life: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the waues where-with hee hath been toſſed, the rocks which he hath eſcaped, the Pyrats, (namely the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and his Angels) whom hee hath happily auoyded. VVhen he ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this tranſitory world to be but a dungeon of ſinners, where the growth of Vertue is poyſoned with the puddle water of penurie, where rancor &amp; deſpight chiefely raigneth, and all goodnes is ouer-whelmed in malice, where vertue is a handmaide to ſugred hypocriſie, ſmooth malice, hidden ambition, ſmiling enuie, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked tyranny. Beſides, when he ſhall behold ſo many thouſand ſoules de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending into hell, and that it hath pleaſed the omnipotent King, among ſo many millions of damned perſons, thou ſhalt be one of that predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16349:40"/>companie, which ſhould obtaine ſuch vnexpreſſable felicitie and glory. Yea what a glorious ſight will it bee to thee, to ſee ſo many perſons hauing on their heads golden Crownes, and to ſee the Kingly ſeats of heauen filled vp, and that Citty builded, and the noble Ieruſalem repayred againe. Yea what a ioy will it bee to thee, to ſee Archangells, Angells, the ſoules of Saints, the companie of Martirs, the Sunne, the Moone, the gliſtering Starres, and all other things, each one of them in their courſe and qualitie, ſhowe themſelues obedient to his will, giuing veneration, glory, and praiſe, ſinging this ſweete ſong, praiſe, and honor, and power, and glory bee vnto him, that ſitteth vppon the Throne, and vnto the Lambe for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore.</p>
                  <p>Is not this a glorious companie? a ioyfull countrey; a happy life; who ſhall be theſe ſo fortunate, and ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16349:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>that are elected for thee. Happy ſhall I be, if the remnant of my poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, might come to ſee the clearenes of this Ieruſalem. To behold her gates wrought with Emeraldes, and Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phires, and all the circuit of her walls built with precious ſtones, her ſtreetes paued with poliſhed marble, and in all her parts ſhall be ſung Alleluia. It ſeemeth a preſumption to deſire thee, and yet I will not liue without the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of thee, for by the grace of God, (which grace I hope in Chriſt ſhall more and more daily abound in mee) I purpoſe to refuſe no labours, paines, and trauels, ſo that at the end of my naturall life my ſoule may reſt with my Redeemer. Let tribulations afflict me: let diſeaſes moleſt mee; let my daies be conſumed with weeping, and teares alwaies runne downe by my cheekes; let mee alwaies drinke the bitter wormewoode water of aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; let lamentation and mourning al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16349:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>accompanie me: let me be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted with captiuitie. Nay let my head be cut off with <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt, or let mee be ſtoned to death with <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen:</hi> yea let my eies be pulled out of my head, or my fleſh be torced with pincers; let vexations poure downe as thicke as haile, ſo that all that paſſe by may behold and ſee: if there bee any ſorrowe like vnto my ſorrowe. Yet all theſe griefes would I willingly ſuſtaine, if it would pleaſe my God, that when pal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> death ſhall ſhut vp the eies of my body, that my eies of my ſoule might ſtill behold, and looke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my Red emer. And that when I ſhall bee ſtripped out of this mortall weede, and turned both out of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and houſeroome of this world, yet at laſt I may arriue at that bleſſed Hauen, the celeſtiall Ieruſalem, there to be placed among the glorious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the holy Angells and Saints, &amp; receiue an immortall &amp; incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16349:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>crowne of glory. For what will it grieue a man, to haue a troubleſome-night, ſo that ioy commeth in the morning. The Mariner will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard a ſhort tempeſt, ſo that preſently after the ſtorm, there followeth a quiet calme: euen ſo ſhould it ſeeme to vs. Although for a ſhort ſeaſon we ſuffer ſorrowe in this world, yet for that ſhort ſorrowe wee ſhall reape euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ioy. Therefore let vs conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endure to the end of our ſorrowes, for he that endureth to the end, ſhall be ſaued. Would we not eſteeme him a fooliſh man, who would refuſe to ſuffer patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly the tortures of one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo that after, hee ſhould inioy perpetuall happineſſe.</p>
                  <p>VVell ſaith S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> So great is the fairenes, and pleaſure of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall light, that if one might not liue there longer then one day, for thys onely, innumerable yeeres full of the delights of this life, and aboundance
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16349:42"/>of temporall goods, he might rightly &amp; worthily be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented. For in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, we ſhal haue light without end, brightneſſe without comprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, peace without inuaſion. In this world our ſences are benummed, &amp; frozen with the extremitie of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries coldneſſe, but in heauen there ſhal ſuch vnexpected bliſſe ſhine vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs, that all the parts of our body and ſoule ſhal be miraculouſly cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the lightning of ſelicitie. In this world, if the whole worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all humane creatures vvere compriſed in the globe of one mans breaſt, yet were not that one man ſo happy, as the leaſt Saint in Heauen. In this world wee are but as it vvere ſhips without a Pylot, tumbling vp and downe in vncertaine waues, till we runne vpon the rocks of ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, or bee ouerthrowne by the ſtormie winde of forraine inuaſion: In this VVorld we are but as it were
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16349:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>tenisbals, toſſed by the racked of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious fortune, but in heauen vve need not feare the tempeſts of aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, for there wee ſhall dwell vvith Saints vnited in perfection; there we ſhall taſt the golden fruite of bleſſed ſoules: there wee ſhal haue Chriſt a guide vnto our waies, and a Gardian to our perſons; there Chriſt ſhall be light vnto our eyes, muſick vnto our eares, ſweetnes to our taſt, content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to our ſoules.</p>
                  <p>The ſtate of the Church militant, heere in this world, is like the Arke floting vpon waters, like a lilly grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing among thornes, like Chriſts ſhip in the 8 of <hi>Mathew,</hi> couered vvith waues, and yet not drowned: But in the ſecond worlde it ſhall be trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, where it ſhal gloriouſly raigne for euermore. Man in this world is but an Anatomy of miſery, or a ſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle of a dolorous ending tragedie, but in the world to come, he ſhall be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16349:43"/>a paragon of glory, and a patterne of endleſſe happineſſe. Therefore, ſith the reward of our godly endeuours, ſhal be ſo well recompenced in the future life, let vs abandon all vicious pleaſures, &amp; neuer be recalled to the vomit of carnall deſires: Let vs fight manfully vnder the banner of our grand captaine Chriſt, vntill we van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh all his enemies, the denill &amp; his angels: and for that good ſeruice per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in Chriſtes quarrell, we ſhall receiue at his handes a large pay, namely, an euerlaſting life, and an immortall crowne of glory.</p>
                  <p>Now therefore, ſith I haue (as it were) lighted a candle to the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſun-ſhine of this heauenly glorie. which cannot any way be better ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed out, with the beſt penſil, then by couering it ouer with the vaile of ſilence, I will ſpeake but verie little more concerning this happines, but will onely compare the torments of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16349:44"/>hell to the ioyes of heauen. For as beautie ſeemes more excellent, when it is paralelled with deformitie, ſo wil heauen ſhow more glorious when it is compared to hell. For as it is an ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iome with the Logicians, Of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie things the reaſon is contrarie: ſo in this contrarietie in heauen, and in hell, hee which doth perceiue the ioyes in heauen, may eaſily coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture at the torments in hell.</p>
                  <p>If the ioyes in heauen cannot bee expreſſed by the tongues of Angells, then the torments of hell cannot be declared by the beſt Orator. For as thoſe two places be diſtant in quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſo their ioyes and paines be equall in quantitie. If that the ioyes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen be infinite, the paines of hel muſt conſequently followe to be infinite. Now then, ſith theſe two oppoſite places bee diſtinguiſhed with ſuch a contrarietie, the ioyes of the one e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man would gladly enioy, the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16349:44"/>paines of the other, euery man would willingly eſchewe, it followeth that this is the greateſt impediment for a man, not willingly to welcome death, becauſe he is wonderfully afraid, leaſt he ſhould bee punniſhed for his ſinnes in theſe helliſh torments: theſe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments doe ingender ſuch a feare in a man, that hee horridly quaketh at the mention of death.</p>
                  <p>For when a man ſhall recount with himſelfe that he offered the May crop of his life to the deuill, that hee ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his blooming yeares to the ſeruice of the deuill, and that now the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of his youth are blaſted, the fruite perriſh, the body of the Tree groweth to decay, then hee ſhall thinke with himſelfe, that hee being voyde of the ſap of good fruites, ſhall become fuell for hell fire. When he ſhall lie on his departing bed, burdened with the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy loade of his treſpaſſes, and vexed with the worme of conſcience, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16349:45"/>feeling the crampe of death wreſting his harts ſtrings, and ready inpathed in his finally voyage, and not farre from the period of his daies. Oh how hee ſhall be diſtracted in his ſenſes, when he ſhould make a free gift of his body and ſoule to God, and by bequeath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to diſpach the whole menage of all eternitie, and of the treaſures of heauen: Oh how ſhall he bee mazed, when he ſhall conſider, how the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning pleaſures of his youth lulled him a ſleepe in ſinne, how the violent heat of the noone of his age did prouoke and excite ſinfull affections, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the coole and calme of his eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, how can hee hope to retire to a Chriſtian reſt, and cloſe vp the day of his life with a cleare ſunſet, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the light of grace, without which euery one ſhall abide in euerlaſting darkeneſſe. Theſe conſiderations I ſay, will make a man tremble at the mention of death: for <hi>peccati ſtipendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16349:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>mors,</hi> the reward of ſinne is death, and theſe torments in hell fire; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when hee ſhall thinke with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that the moſt vertuous, can ſcarce attaine to heauen in mountenance of yeares, whoſe liues were died in the beautifull graine of vertue, how then ſhall hee wretched ſinner hope to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine heauen, ſince all his life time hee hath perſeuered in ſinne, &amp; that now death hauing taken away abilitie in ſinning, and left him to the lees of his dying daies, how ſhall he beleiue to be infranchiſed in that heauenly Citty, which is not ſo penurious of friends, that it ſhould bee made ſalable for the refuſe and reuerſion of euery ſinners life. A King which hath liued like an Epicure heere vppon earth, and in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing tooke delight, but like a Nero to oppreſſe the innocent; ſhall not inioy the heauenly happineſſe. (For as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith) It is impoſsible to ioyne preſent, and future delights. And as
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16349:46"/>the ſame father in another place ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. He that is fed with earthly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, is counted vnworthy of eternall ioyes; The ſhining title of worldly glory, ſhall nothing helpe to the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines of that life: they be like bladders which are puffed vp with the winde of proſperitie, and only doe affect the ſmoke of vaine glory; they doe not obſerue the precept, giuen by <hi>Moſes</hi> vnto Princes, Princes muſt reade the Lawe all the daies of their liues, and as <hi>Ioſua,</hi> let not the booke of this Lawe depart out of thy mouth, but record therein day and night. Their Lawes ſhould be axioms, ariſing out of their owne deedes, but they themſelues are the readieſt to infring the ſame. Now then when the leaſe of the liues of theſe Stewards, who hold all their poſſeſsions by ſeruice, is expired, and ſhall be ſummoned by death, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before their Land-lord to giue there accounts, how beneficially they
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:16349:46"/>haue imployed their talents, then they will beginne to haue a feeling ſenſe of there owne miſerie, ſeeing how ill they did gouerne the people, ouer the which the Lord had made them ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers.</p>
                  <p>We reade that <hi>Dauid</hi> being choſen of God, to feede his people in <hi>Iacob,</hi> and his in heritance in Iſraell, did feede them according to the ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his hart, and guided thee by the diſcretion of his handes. Theſe <hi>Dauids</hi> be few now adaies; and as the Poeth ſaith,</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Rex bonus est ſapiens, qualem vix rep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perit vnum,</l>
                     <l>Mellibus e cunctis hominum conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus <hi>Apollo.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <p>A good King and wiſe, ſuch a one as <hi>Apollo,</hi> beeing asked counſell of, coulde ſcarce finde one among all men.</p>
                  <p>Yet thanks be giuen to God, who by his bleſſed prouidence hath elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16349:47"/>a ſecond Dauid to raigne ouer vs, whoſe loynes are girded with righteouſneſſe, and faithfulneſſe the buckle of his raines: in whoſe throne <hi>Astraea</hi> ſits weying euery mans mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits by the equall ballance of their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whoſe minde is inuironed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vice, with the cleere ſtreames of ſweet vertue. And therefore, ſith it hath pleaſed God to ſet a temporal &amp; tranſitory crowne of glorie on his head, he needs not feare, but that in the world to come, he ſhall be crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a farre ſurpaſsing weight of glorie, &amp; there ſhall taſt the heauenly Manna, and drinke the nectar of ioy: But as for other Princes, who heere doe taſt the Roſes of proſperitie, ſhal in the world to come, for their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe drinke the worme-wood of aduerſitie: when they ſhall recount with themſelues, that they haue tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the Lords annointed, and done his Prophets harme, iniured the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16349:47"/>oppreſſed the innocent, prophaned the ſanctuary of God, &amp; onely delighted themſelues with the vaine pompe of this world, how can they hope that their impure ſoules ſhoulde bee tranſlated to this pure place of endleſſe comfort? So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to deſcend lower by a lineall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, throughout all the pedigrees of men. Behold the Miniſterie, who haue the ouer-ſight of our ſoules, ſee if they can boldly run vnto the goale of death, who haue not ledde theyr liues according to their inioyned vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations. The Miniſters, which ſhould haue two eyes, (as <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith) one of famous learning, the other of an vpright &amp; godly life; many of them haue one of theſe eyes, but want the other. And as the ſame <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, Many declare that in wordes, vvhich in life and manners they goe againſt. Theſe haue the eye of learning, but want the eye of honeſt life. Yea ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16349:48"/>are blinde of both eyes, but they be worſe then the former: For the Miniſters ſhould by their endeuours and honeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation, reclaime the wicked from the brink of perdition, they ſhould inuent medicinable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits againſt the goſtly maladies of ſinners: they ſhould in the generall famine of ſpirituall foode, prepare with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> abundance of the breade of Angels, for the repaſt of theyr ſoules.</p>
                  <p>Yea, they ſhould ſtudie ſpirituall Phiſicke, and be trauelled in the ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinie of the ſoules diſeaſes, and be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the beating and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of euery mans pulſe: they ſhould purge theyr flock from the leaproſie of ſinne; they ſhould lift vp theyr voyce like a trumpet, and ſhewe the people their offences, and the houſe of <hi>Iacob</hi> theyr ſinnes. They are the Prophets of the Lord, that ſhal bring the meſſages from the Mountaines,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16349:48"/>and proclaime peace. They be the light of the VVorlde, the ſalt of the earth; they be watch-men, which for <hi>Sions</hi> ſake ſhould not holde theyr tongues, &amp; for <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> ſake ſhould not ceaſe.</p>
                  <p>Nowe when they ſhall remember that they haue beene dumbe dogges, which did not bark, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wolues did teare their flocks. And as <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, Thou haſt ſeene the wolfe and haſt eſcaped, ſaying, by chance I haue eſcaped all: Thou haſt eſcaped be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt kept ſilence: Thou haſt been heere in body, thou haſt eſcaped in ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>Or as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, when they ſhall remember, they were <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistri Christi, ſed ſerni anti Christi,</hi> or call to mind the ſtraight commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t giuen by chriſt to <hi>Peter,</hi> to feede Chriſtes flocke, and they haue been rather wolues the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhepheards, which did rather fleece and oppreſſe them,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16349:49"/>then protect them: when they did imitate, Souldiers in habit, husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in gaine, indeede they were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe they did neither fight againſt the Wolues as Souldiers, nor as husbandmen labour in Gods Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde, nor as Clarkes preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell in the Church, and while they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire both, they confound both. As <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith: therefore their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences will be perplixed, their mindes diſtracted, nor ſhall they perceiue, the melodious harmonie of excuſing thoughts, or perſwade themſelues of that comfortable aſſurance, that the opening of the booke will ſhowe, that their names are written in heauen, or ſhall they taſt that continuall feaſt, of a cleere conſcience, the ſoules bleſſed banquet; they ſhall wring their hands for griefe, when they might haue clapt for ioy, they ſhall tremble, when they might haue triumph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, they ſhall weepe, when they might haue laught,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16349:49"/>they ſhall wiſh that the Mountaines would couer them, &amp; hide them from the ſight of God: and theſe bee the cauſes, why ſo vnwillingly they yeeld to dy, yea euen whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their forces lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh, their ſenſes impaire, their body droupeth, and on euery ſide the rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous cottage, of their fraile body threatneth a fall, yea when they may behold their graſſe waſted, their grapes gathered, their houſe broken, and nothing remaining but the ſtocke of the grapes, the skinne of the fleſh, and but one only blaſt of life, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they will ſay with <hi>Calli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machus,</hi> I am too old to liue, and too young to die; and they are afraid to cloſe vp their eies, when they heare the Bell of death knelling in their eares: but had rather fight ſtill in this Campe of miſerie, then by deaths paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pot, to bee conducted out of this world. They had rather with <hi>Ariſtip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> prolong life, then with <hi>Socrates</hi>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:16349:50"/>yield to die; and the cauſes bee theſe, becauſe they haue not beene carefull in their functions, but haue beene careleſſe in their liues, diſſolute in their actions: they were not the inſtruments of God, hauing a ſound to teach well, but the bones of the deuill, becauſe they did want the feeling: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they hauing deuoted their liues, only to the deuill, their conſcience doe aſſure them, that they hauing gorged the deuill, with the faireſt fruites of their liues, God will not feede vppon the ſcrappes of his leauings, &amp; gleane the reproofe of his harueſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they bee vnwilling to depart out of this life.</p>
                  <p>But to paſſe ouer the ſpirituall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors, and come to ciuell Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates: The Lawyers they make the lawes and ſtatutes limetwiggs, to catch the ſimple, which ſhould bee as it were Sea-markes to auoyde ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke, for ignorant paſſengers; they
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:16349:50"/>ſtuddie for to inuent, pollicie, how to palliate committed diſorders. The Iudges imitate <hi>Samuels</hi> ſongs, which did not walke in their fathers waies, but tooke bribes and rewards to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert right. The widdowes complaine, the Orphans are wronged, the poore are not regarded. And (as <hi>Iſidorus</hi> ſaith) through the loue of deſire, lawes are of no force, hee that hath to giue, hath alſo to gouerne. And (as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith) a fat Hen doth more preuaile with Iudges then iuſtice, and money more then innocencie. They will not regard any plea, vnleſſe the euidence containes golden eloquence. But there is another commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment giuen them in Deutronomie, Wreſt not the law, nor know any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, neither take any rewards, for giftes, blind the wiſe, and peruert the words of the righteous: &amp; as there is a common axiom among the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſts, <hi>Ni nire non debet eſſe acceptio
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:16349:51"/>perſonarum:</hi> the Iudges, and Lawyers ſhould not regard the great men more then the poore, nor the plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifes bagges, more then the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, <hi>in forma pauperis.</hi> Woe be vnto them that make vnrighteous lawes, whereby the poore are oppreſſed. Woe vnto that abominable Cittie, whoſe Rulers are as roaring Lyons, whoſe Iudges are as Wolues in the Eucning: theſe threatnings out of the Scripture, will make the Lawyers ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous to die, when they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count with themſelues, how oft they haue trangreſſed theſe diuine lawes, how many bribes they haue receiued to giue vniuſt ſentence, how oft they haue ſtopt their eares, againſt the crie of the needie, how oft they haue heard the accuſer, &amp; would not hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the accuſed. Reiecting <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> graue iudgement, who did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſtop one of his eares, when any one did complaine againe another,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:16349:51"/>ſaying, this care I lend the accuſer, the other I reſerue for the excuſer. When I ſay they ſhall record their publicke and priuate iniuries, their conniuence at manifeſt faults, and too much ſeueritie at ſmall crimes, their vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full condemnations, and their partiall abſolutions, I ſay theſe committed of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences will ſo examinate them, and ſtrike ſuch a terror into them, when the ſtreame of their life runneth at a low ebbe, and the date of their life heere in this world is expired, and they entering into the kalends of death, then they will ſit quiuering for feare, and knocke at the doore of their conſcience, and there ſummon a queſt of inquirie for their ſinnes, and when they ſhall come to appeare at the Bar of conſideration, and there be arrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, they ſhall anſwere as priſoners at the Barre, guiltie, guiltie. And this is the reaſon why they are ſo vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to depart out of this life: in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16349:52"/>like manner the Tradeſmen, who are cuſtomers to the world, who haue gotten falſe ware ſutable to the ſhoppe of ſuch Marchants, whoſe traficke is to toile, whoſe wealth traſh, whoſe gaine miſerie: they I ſay, are vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to depart this life, becauſe by their fraudulent dealings, they haue pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed an ill conſcience, which doth make them ſleepe like the Nightin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galls, who alwaies ſleepe with a prickt againſt their breſt, ſo doe they ſleepe, or rather ſlumber, hauing a pricking conſcience. It alwaies regiſtreth their miſdeedes, ſhowing them their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and ſo they haue no confident perſwaſiion that their election is ſure. Alſo the husbandmen, who haue long time tilled the earth, and by the ſweat of their labours, haue increaſed their worldly poſſeſsions, &amp; now perceiue by the infirmitie of their body, they bee not able any more to endure the churliſh entertainment of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:16349:52"/>world, or to prolong the tedious line of life, and recount with themſelues what infinite paines they haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone, for to obtaine worldly riches, and neuer laboured one houre in the field of Gods Church, to poſſeſſe beauenly treaſures, ſowing the ſeedes of repentant ſorrowe, and watering them with the teares of contrition, that they might reape a more benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall harueſt, and gather the fruits of endleſſe comfort.</p>
                  <p>Then they will thinke with them ſelues, that it is an vnſeaſonable time to alter the courſe of their vnthri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing husbandry, when in the Aprill of theyr yeeres they might haue brought foorth the flowers &amp; fruites of ſaluation, and theſe be the cauſes why they be vnwilling to depart out of this life, and dare not ſay with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Simeon,</hi> O Lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund that my Soule may depart in peace. Nor dare not cry out with Dauid, the pyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16349:53"/>of mother <hi>Sion,</hi> who liued in the child-hood of the Church, when the clowde of the Law did ouerſhadow the appearance of the Sun in fulneſſe of comfort, before Chriſt had ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the ſtore-houſe of ioy; and yet he beeing wearie of his life, and the burden of his body, cryed out, Oh howe long ſhall I liue in this priſon? And <hi>Paule,</hi> the notable organ of the holy Ghoſt, ſingeth the ſame long with Dauid, ſaying; ô wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from this body of ſinne? So did Father <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie</hi> wiſh, that the wombe had ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for his tombe. And ſo did <hi>Eſay</hi> be waile his birth, and murmured a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the knees that held him vp, &amp; the breaſts that gaue him ſucke. For they knew that the worlde was but a ſea of ſorrow, and our life like vnto a new ſhip put into the ſea, fleeting to the bottomleſſe ſwallow, where as the tempeſtuous winds and waues of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16349:53"/>this world doe beate vppon, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies threaten a drowning of life: but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this fraile mortall life ſeemes to haue broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her wings by the force of death, then preſently as immortall ſhee taketh her flight, and lands at a good port: VVhy therefore ſhould wee deſire to adde more feathers to the wings of time, ſith after our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution we ſhal be made liuely mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, fully knit in our body Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                  <p>Ay but a man will ſay, if I were fully perſwaded, that I ſhould bee made partaker of this beauenlie life, I would willingly deſire to die, and wiſh that the feeble threds of my life would euery howre vntwine: But now my guiltie conſcience doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe mee, my ill ledde life doth terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie me, and all my wicked deedes doe ſo moleſt my mind, that I am afraide to die. Sure this ſerious conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our former offences, dooth
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:16349:54"/>much amaze a good grounded chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, when hee lies vppon his dying bed, wayting for the rufull diuorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his body and ſoule, hauing a fettered conſcience, which alwaies will aſſure him, that he hauing been a ſluggiſh drone in the hiue of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes Church, ſhall not taſt the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of pleaſure, nor the hony combe of comfort in the heauenly Citty, but hee ſhall bee glutted with the ſower grape of perſecution, of Gods wrath, and theſe helliſh torments: that he hauing been a careleſſe Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riner in this world, and alwaies the ſhippe of his body remaining in the ſcope of the wicked wind and vvea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this world, the Pirate the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill ſhall make ſhipwracke of his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and ſo hee perriſh vppon the rocks of eternall ruine.</p>
                  <p>But againſt all theſe deſperable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, the ſaying of Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> is the beſt remedy, If thou feare
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:16349:54"/>iudgement to come, rebuke thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. In the whole courſe of thy life ſo liue, that thou maiſt haue a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure conſcience: for thou muſt liue here for a time in ſuch ſort, that thou dying godly, maiſt liue for euer. VVe muſt die that wee may liue, and wee muſt liue that wee may die well. If thou liueſt well, thou ſhalt die vvell, and thou ſhalt liue wel, if thou dooſt follow the holy courſe which Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> obſerued, VVhether I eate or drinke (ſaith hee) or what ſoeuer els I doe, alwaies that ſame terrible trumpet ſoundeth in mine eares, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe you that be dead, and come to iudgement. For as the ſame Father ſaith in another place, He eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temneth all things, that doth alwaies thinke that he ſhall die.</p>
                  <p>For he that alwaies takes the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of death for his vnſeparable ſpouſe, and bitter ſighs for his chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and holy compunction for his
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:16349:55"/>mother to depure him from his filthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he which hateth the world per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, fauoreth godlineſſe zealouſly, endeuoreth to amend his life ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, obeieth his ſuperiors gladly, and beareth Chriſts croſſe patiently, ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth good tokens that hee will die a good Chriſtian: ſuch a man needs not feare the mention of death, nor neede his ſoule weepe in ſecret, nor his eies drop downe teares, for hee may bee certaine that he is one of that perdeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated company, which ſhall raigne for euermore. But as for a man that hath liued diſſolutely, &amp; through the whole courſe of his life, hath beene a notorious ſinner, yet for all that hee needs not diſpaire; for Chriſt was not ſurpriſed with a rauing feuer, when in the tragedie of his paſsion, he made his body as a Cloude to reſolue in ſhowres of innocent bloud, and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his decreſt vaines to be launced, to giue a full iſſue for the price of our
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:16349:55"/>ſoules redemption. Hee came not to call the righteous, but ſinners to repentance. O yee ſinners, behold the Lambe blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and ſhedding his precious blood to clenſe you from ſinne, and to ſaue you from ſathan, drinke vp in faith the drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings of his blood, and moiſten your ſoules therewith, eate him and chew him, for he is the bread of life, which whoſoeuer eateth, ſhall neuer hunger more. Say with <hi>Chriſtestome, Omnis mea ſalus in paſsione Christi est poſita.</hi> For whatſoeuer doth belong to my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, <hi>paratum est per Chriſti mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> as the ſame father ſaith: his death hath made a ſufficient ranſome for my ſinnes; It is the Lambe of God which doth purge mee from all my ſinnes: I fully beleiue that therefore all my ſinnes ſhall be forgiuen me, not for my merrits, but for Chriſts death, not for my righteouſneſſe, but for Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, which doth extend to thouſands, and tenne thouſands, whoſe ſinnes in
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:16349:56"/>reſpect of Gods mercies, are but (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith) one droppe in reſpect of the whole Sea. And (as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith) the mercie of God is greater, then any miſerie of ours. Hold vp thine eies to heauen, behold the God of all conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and mercy, craue of him to poure downe the influences of his comfort to helpe thy vnbeliefe, to confirme thy faith, to ſtrengthen thee with a ſtedfaſt aſſurance of his heauenly Kingdome. Waſt away thy wickedneſſe in the Fountaine of repentance, and the lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of thy ſinne, in the ſtreaming Riuers of penitent teares. For this heauenly dew of repentance neuer falls, but the Sun of righteouſneſſe drawes it vp; for it was ſweetly vttered by a Diuine of ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt vtterance, that repentant eies are the Cellars of Angells, and penitent teares the ſweeteſt wines, which the ſauour of life perfumeth, the taſt of grace ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and the pureſt cullours of retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning innocency highly beautifieth. Oh
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:16349:56"/>that our harts were euermore ſuch a lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becke, diſtilling ſo pure a quinteſſence of godlineſſe, drawne from the weedes of our offences; by the fire of true contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, heauen would mourne at the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of ſo precious waters, and earth la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the loſſe of ſo fruitfull ſhowres. Sure till death cloſe vp thoſe fountaines, they ſhould neuer faile running: which if they did alwaies runne, we neede not doubt of our ſaluation, but that GOD would waſh away all our ſinnes. The world (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) had not perriſhed with the flood, if they had betaken them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to repentance. And as it is in <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,</hi> If wee repent of our wickedneſſe, God will repent of his wickedneſſe deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt vs, and as it is in <hi>Ezechiell,</hi> If the vngodly will turne away from all his ſinnes that he hath done, doubtleſſe he ſhall liue and not die. And againe, bee conuerted, and turne you cleane from your wickedneſſe, ſo ſhall there do ſinne doe you harme. So when the Niniuites
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:16349:57"/>did repent, mourning in Sack-cloath and aſhes, he repented on the euill which he ſaid he would doe vnto them, and did it not. Examples of repentant ſinners, who obtained remiſsion for their offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, be <hi>Paule,</hi> the ſinfull woman, <hi>Dauid, Manaſſes, Peter,</hi> the theife this day on the croſſe, this night in Paradiſe. For Ieſus is like an Euangelicall henne, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſeth clocking to gather thee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his winges like a Chicken; for it pleaſed Ieſus of vnmerrited goodneſſe, to leaue the nintie nine miſt ſheepe, the ſocietie of bleſſed Angells, to ſeeke the ſtraying ſheepe, the groate that loſt the royall ſtampe of pure nature: man this loſt ſheepe thou ſoughteſt (O Ieſus) thou foundeſt ſweete Ieſus, by death thou foundeſt him, by bleeding paines thou foundeſt him, by nayled hands and boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red feete thou foundeſt him, by a thornie Crowne, by drinking vineger, by ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting droppes of bloud, by ſuffering the violent death on the croſſe thou foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:16349:57"/>him. O louing Ieſus, and tender harted Samaritan, that of a ſicke haſt ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, of a grieuous ſinner haſt ſaued him, of a wicked creature, haſt waſhed him in the ſtreame of thy ineſtimable mercie. Therfore I confidently beleiue although the flower of my age is faded, the graſſe withered, and my whole life as a vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vapoure is paſſed away, yet when I ſhail be diſſolued, I aſſuredly hope to be ioyned fully to Ieſus my head, and onely Vine, wherein I liue; although the purſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant ſickneſſe muſt viſit this body of ſin, and death muſt rowe mee ouer the Seas of this world, yet I hope in the barke of faith, and merrits of Chriſt Ieſus, and by the Ancor of Gods couenaunts made to the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> I ſhall arriue at that bleſſed Hauen, from whence I ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer more hoiſe vp ſailes, or lanch into the deepe of miſerie, but ſhall ſit imparadiſed in heauen with fulneſſe of grace, till the day of thy great viſitation ſhal com, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meeting thee in the cloudes, I ſhall enter into the ſtore houſe of ioyes, there for
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:16349:58"/>euermore to raigne.</p>
                  <p>If a ſinner could thus abſolutely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme himſelf, &amp; not diſtruſt Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and clemencie, without all doubt he would not feare to die: but withall, hee muſt haue a ſetled determination, to mortifie his bodie, to abandon vices, &amp; with the trumpet of a Chriſtian life to ſound a retraite fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin, alwaies remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring Chriſt crucified: For as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, The remembrance of Chriſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, crucifieth ſinne. And as S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> ſaith, Then Chriſt dooth ſleepe in thee, when thou haſt forgot his paſsion. The readieſt way, &amp; direct path to goe to Heauen, is to ſwim through the red ſea of Chriſtes blood. The droppes of Chriſts precious blood raigning downe from the clowdes of his mercie, muſt que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch the angry flame of Gods wrath, which wee cannot extinguiſh by the vertuous water of any merrit. It is the oyle of Grace, which muſt purge our defiled harts: It is the dewe of heauen which will make vs floriſh, beeing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:16349:58"/>into the true Oliue. It is the welſpring of our ſaluation, it is the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly manna, which all of vs ſhould ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vp in the wildernes of this world. Loue this good thing, in which all goodnes is, &amp; it is enough for thee: yea obſerue but this ſhort leſſon which <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> giueth, &amp; thou art a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian: <hi>Ama deum, et amices in deum, et ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micos propter deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et beatus es,</hi> Loue Chriſt who loueth thee, loue his friends, that loue Chriſt, and thee, loue Chriſtes ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that hate Chriſt and thee, &amp; then thou ſhalt be beloued of Chriſt; for lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him, thou ſhalt bee beloued of Chriſt: for louing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hate Chriſt, &amp; thee, the haters ſhall perriſh, yet thou louing, ſhalt be beloued. Loue GOD without meaſure, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalt thou be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py without meaſure. Loue God withal thy hart, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſhalt behold with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end, loue without pride, praiſe with out wearines. Therfore, if men did but obſerue this briefe leſſon, wee need not feare death, but welcome him vvith a
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:16349:59"/>thouſand kiſſes, for that meſſenger doth bring vs gladde tidings; for by him we change tranſitory, mortall, and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible things, for certaine, immortall, and incorruptible treaſures, earth for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſin for godlines, darknes for light, feare for ſecurity, trauell for quietneſſe, ſickneſſe for health, death for life, the company of men, for the companie of the omnipotent God, and heauenly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, the vile pleaſures of this world, for the ineſtimable ioyes of heauen.</p>
                  <p>Oh therefore let vs hartily wiſh to be loſoned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this life, that we may come to appeare before the preſence of God: let vs ſay with <hi>Dauid,</hi> Like as the Hart deſireth the water brookes, ſo longeth my ſoule after thee, ô God, O GOD, thou art my God, early will I ſeek thee, my ſoule thirſteth for thee, my fleſh alſo longeth after thee, in a barren and dry land where no water is. Let vs ſay with <hi>Iob,</hi> It grieueth my ſoule to liue longer in this mortall body. Let vs ſay with holy <hi>Toby,</hi> O Lord deale with me accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:16349:59"/>to thy will, and command my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to be receiued in peace. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the liuely threds of our life vntie, the ſpin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle vndoe, the web riue, and our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life endeth, yet the ſpirituall and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall part, namely the ſoule, ſhall be receiued with Angels, &amp; carried to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen moſt louingly, as a precious relique into the kingdome of heauen. It ſhal be like a Doue carried on the wings of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, into this heauenly Palace: For as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, It is the office of Angels to carry ſoules to the company of the bleſſed. Now therefore, when Death ſhal breake vp your mortall houſe, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print this leſſon in the forefront of your languiſhing fleſh, yea euen when you are halfe bereſt of life, that you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Chriſt crucified; remember him to be the onely Sauiour; remember God the Father, to bee a moſt mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Fixe the eyes of your faith on Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, &amp; on his merrits, on his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion &amp; death, on his bleſſed body brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and his moſt precious blood ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:16349:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>on his triumph and victory ouer fathan, and his helliſh army. Forget not that all your ſinnes are waſhed away in Chriſtes blood, &amp; that by vertue of his death and paſsion, you are made beyre of euerlaſting ſaluation. Fight a good fight, be not diſcouraged by the paines of death, neuer ſhrink in Deaths battell, call vppon Ieſus, for no baulme will be more comfortable to a wound, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of Ieſus to deaths wound. Put on the Helmet of ſaluation, the breſt-plate of righteouſnes, the girdle of truth, the ſhield of faith, the ſworde of the ſpirit, and your feete ſhod with the preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goſpell of peace. Feare not, ſtand faſt, quit your ſelues like men, for in this ſpirituall battell, you ſight vnder the banner of the mighty &amp; victorious Emperor Ieſus Chriſt; onely continue with theſe weapons, &amp; the day is yours. If ſathan tempt you, you may with har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie prayers, (good Orators for your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation) inchant that Dragon, that hee may ſleep, while your ſoule is tranſlated
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:16349:60"/>to taſt of the golden fruite of bleſſed ſoules: perſeuere in this battell, which is the true complement of vertue: The paine of the battel is ſmall, the glorie of the triumph ſhall abide for euer &amp; euer. For ſo ſaith the ſcripture, To him that ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mmeth, I will giue to eate of the tree of life, which is in the midſt of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice: be faithful vnto the death, and I wil giue thee a crowne of life. Hee that ouercommeth, I wil make a piller in the temple of my God, and hee ſhall go no more out: yea to him that ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>math wil I grant to ſit with me in my ſeate.</p>
                  <p>Theſe precious promiſes &amp; rewards, may make vs couragious againſt death: folow your captaine Chriſt &amp; you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre, for he is the way, belieue chriſt &amp; you cannot be deceiued for hee is the truth, abide and remaine in Chriſt, and you cannot die the death euerlaſting, for he is the life: wherfore cleaue with ſtrong faith to Chriſt, and ſay with that wiſe man; My minde is rooted and built in Chriſt, and then you neede not feare
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:16349:61"/>when death ſhall giue your ſoule the winges of true libertie, to depart out of your fraile fleſh, and to flie vp to heauen, and reſt within <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome: for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſhal reſt from your labors &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels. For ſo ſaith the ſcripture; the ſoules of the righteous are in thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ô God, &amp; the paine of death ſhall not touch them. In the ſight of the vnwiſe they appeare to die, but they are in peace; they are as the Angells of God: they are clad with white garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; haue golden crownes vpon their heads. They doe ſtand day &amp; night before his Maieſty, there they haue all ioy, ſolace, and harts contentments. By death we paſſe from earth to heauen, from men to Angells, from warre to peace, from paine to pleaſure, from griefe to gladneſſe, from miſerie to perpetuall felicitie: we paſſe by death from this life, which is like a bubble in the water, like a weauers Shettell, like a ſmoake, like a vapoure, like a ſhaddowe, like a flower that fadeth, like graſſe that withereth, it is but a ſpan-long: it is a warfare, it is
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:16349:61"/>like a ruinous houſe euer readie to fall, it is like a cloude in the element, whereof wee are vncertaine, where and when it falleth. This cloude ſometimes melteth in the cradle, ſometimes in the chaire. Death is like the Sunne, whenſoeuer it ſhineth, it melteth our cloudie life, be the cloude thereof neuer ſo thicke or thin in yeares: this life is like an vncertaine we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thercocke, which turnech at euery blaſt; like a Waue that mounteth at euery ſtorme: like a reede that boweth at eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry whiſtling wind. This world is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile, a vale of miſerie, a wilderneſſe of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, a dungeon of ſinners, a ſea of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, where wee paſſe away the wauer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing daies of this vncertaine life, ſayling as Pilgrims on the waters of this world, toſſed by the tempeſts of aduerſitie, and oppreſſed by ſundry Pyrats, the fleſh, ſin, and the deuill, and yet by the Barke of a liuely faith, and by the Marriner death, wee ſhall bee tranſported from the fleſh pots of Egipt, to eate of comfortable Manna, not in the wilderneſſe, but in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:16349:62"/>new Ieruſalem: Therefore haſt ô good God to deliuer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this painfull life, to that glorious life, from this wretched manſion, to that excellent tabernacle: from this ſtormie worlde, to the calme country of heauen; where I ſhall haue liberty without impriſonment, health without ſicknes, ioy without ſorrowe, pleaſure without paine, in ſuch ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, eternitie, and perpetuitie, as paſſeth all thoughts. Come therefore Death, thou art welcome, thou art thrice wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come death.</p>
                  <p>For when the Tree of my life ſhall fall downe heere vpon earth, and I ſhall ſee my father duſt, &amp; my mother aſhes, yer my ſoule ſhall be carried into <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> boſome. Adiew vile life, farewell life, ſinfull life adiewe: and welcome Death, the Embaſſador from my louing Sauiour: for by thee my miſery ſhall end. So that (O Death) thou art wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. VVelcome ſicknes, for my Lord Ieſus hath nowe ſent thee to fetch mee from this priſon to his Pallace, from a
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:16349:62"/>ſtrange pilgrimage, to dwell in the reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Country of <hi>Canaan,</hi> from theſe teares and mourning, to the day of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage (ſweet Ieſus) to bee eſpouſed to thee in thy merrits for euermore, where I ſhall liue like a Demie-god, hauing the ſight of the glorious Trinitie, and the companie of holie Patriarks, Prophets, Apoſtles, Martirs, and bleſſed Saints, &amp; inherite ſuch ioyes, as neither eye hath ſeene, nor eare hath heard, nor hart e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer conceiued.</p>
                  <p>Therefore welcome death, welcome ſweet death, for thou ſhalt remooue me out of this priſon, &amp; deliuer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this body of ſinne, to enter into the amiable tabernacles of my Lord, where one day is better then a thouſand elſe-where: I ſhal no more weep by the waters of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon, when I ſhal remember thee ô <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> for now I ſhall be in <hi>Sion,</hi> and dwell there for euermore. Come therfore, ô death to mee at thy pleaſure, for it is a pleaſure for me to die, com death, ô my ioy, for it is a ioy for mee to enioy thee.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:16349:63"/>VVelcome death the beginning of ioy, the firſt fruite of pleaſure, when thou commeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar well ſorowes, adiew miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, death is the Prince of delights. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe therfore &amp; make haſt ô my beloued, my delight, my comfort, for at thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming my winter is paſt, and the tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous waters of miſeries are ceaſed: thou art io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es meſſenger, and gladde ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings bringer, ô life thou art my death, ô death thou art my life: this life is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tintia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ll death, but after this death hath ceaſed vpon my body, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal my ſoule go vnto her life. Adiew therfore, ô my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, welcome, thrice welcome death; farewell alſo ô death, welcome immortall life.</p>
                  <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16349:63"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
